<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="custom.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The article "First Ladies of Colored America" from the Crisis magazine</title>
            <author>Editor Roy Wilkins on behalf of The Crisis magazine</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription, edition, and encoding</resp>
               <name>Michael "Dean" Rice</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This document forms part of the project "Editing the Eartha M.M. White Archive" at the University of North Florida.</p>            
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <region>Florida</region>                  
                  <settlement>Jacksonville</settlement>                  
                  <repository>University of North Florida, Thomas G. Carpenter Library Special Collections and Archives</repository> 
                  <collection>Eartha M.M. White Collection</collection>
                  <idno>Folder D1, Item 329, p. 287 and 289</idno>                  
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc>
                     <p>The following documents are two pages out of the September, 1942 publication of The Crisis magazine. Documents are in good condition. Documents are print and approximately 9 inches by 12 inches.</p>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
     </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <editorialDecl>
           <p>This file was transcribed and encoded according to the editorial criteria of the project "Editing the Eartha M.M. White Archive." Using the various options encoded within &lt;choice&gt; elements, this file enables the viewing of a diplomatic transcription and a regularized reading text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="1" facs="../images/ew_d1_329_287-289_001.jpg"/>
         <p>September, 1942 <hi rend="right"><choice><orig>287</orig><reg/></choice></hi>
         </p>
         <div>
         <head rend="center"><hi rend="xx-large">First Ladies</hi><lb/>
            <hi rend="xx-large">of Colored America</hi><lb/></head>
         </div>
      <div>
            
               <p rend="indent">
                  Throughout <name type="person_group">American</name> history <name type="person_group">colored women</name> have played a most<lb/>
                significant role in the development of our civilization. Because their<lb/>
                early ties with <name type="place" subtype="continent">Africa</name> were abruptly severed (unlike those of their<lb/>
                  <name type="person_group">white sisters</name> with <name type="place" subtype="continent">Europe</name>) and because their greater struggle for<lb/>
               survival compelled a speedier adaptation to the new life here, they<lb/>
               have placed their imprint indelibly on our national life. They are the<lb/>
               chief repository of <name type="person_group">Anglo-Saxon</name> culture. Some students even hold<lb/>
                  that if every <name type="person_group">white person</name> were to disappear from the <name type="place" subtype="country">United States</name>,<lb/>
               it would continue culturally to be <name type="person_group">Anglo-Saxon</name> with, of course, the<lb/>
               softening and sophisticated touch of <name type="place" subtype="continent">Africa</name>.<lb/>
         </p>
      
         <p rend="indent">
            The <name type="person_group">colored woman</name> is responsible to a large degree for the rapid<lb/>
            adaptation of <name type="person_group">black folk</name> to <name type="person_group">American</name> life, for she conveyed to the less<lb/>
         favored male what she learned by closer association with the best that<lb/>
            the civilized white minority had to offer. Indeed, the <name type="person_group">colored woman</name><lb/>
         has been a more potent factor in shaping <name type="person_group">Negro</name> society than the<lb/>
            <name type="person_group">white woman</name> has been in shaping <name type="person_group">white</name> society because the sexual<lb/>
         caste system has been much more fluid and ill-defined than among<lb/>
            <name type="person_group">whites</name>. <name type="person_group">Colored women</name> have worked <hi rend="italics">with</hi> their men and helped<lb/>
         build and maintain every institution we have. Without their<lb/>
         economic aid and counsel we would have made little if any progress.<lb/>
         Equality of the sexes is an old story in <name type="person_group">Negro</name> life. Aframerica is<lb/>
         even a matriarchy.
      </p>
         
            <p rend="indent">
               Through the church, fraternal organizations, parent-teacher asso<lb break="no"/>
            ciations, <name type="organization"><choice><abbr>NAACP</abbr><expan>National Association for the Advancement of Colored People</expan></choice></name> branches and various social groups, our women<lb/>
            have welded a weak and divided people into a more compact, har<lb break="no"/>
            monious and increasingly powerful group. They rank high in indi<lb break="no"/>
            vidual achievement in all fields, but so persistent is the early pattern<lb/>
            of male precedence in <name type="person_group">American</name> thinking that too often the recogni<lb break="no"/>
            tion due women has been withheld or given grudgingly and<lb/>
            patronizingly.<lb/>
         </p>
         
            <p rend="indent">
               It is the purpose of the photographic series which begins on the<lb/>
            following pages and will continue indefinitely, to correct this imbal<lb break="no"/>
            ance by presenting each month four colored women of recognized<lb/>
            ability and accomplishment who have contributed much to the<lb/>
            progress of civilization in <name type="place" subtype="country">America</name>. <title level="m">The Crisis</title> must perforce make<lb/>
            the appraisal and selection. Space imposes a severe limitation upon<lb/>
            us, so failure of anyone to be recognized here does not imply that<lb/>
               her achievements have not been outstanding.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Again, it is obvious that there will be more selections from the city<lb/>
            than from the country and more from the <name type="place" subtype="region">North</name>, <name type="place" subtype="region">East</name> and <name type="place" subtype="region">West</name> than<lb/>
            from the <name type="place" subtype="region">South</name>. Many outstanding women have migrated from the<lb/>
            <name type="place" subtype="region">South</name> to other parts of the nation where greater opportunities have<lb/>
            heretofore existed. However, we plan to leave no state unrecognized.<lb/>
            Our choice will be catholic, our criteria national or sectional fame.<lb/>
         </p>
         <pb n="2" facs="../images/ew_d1_329_287-289_002.jpg"/>
         <p>September, 1942 <hi rend="right"><choice><orig>289</orig><reg/></choice></hi>
         </p>
         <figure>
            <desc>Taken from University of North Florida Special Collections, Eartha M.M. White Collection, Folder D1, Item 329.</desc><lb/><graphic url="../images/ew_d1_329_287-289_002_001.jpg"></graphic>
         </figure>
         <p>
            <emph rend="case(allcaps)"><name type="person">miss eartha m.m. white</name></emph> is a native and resident of <name type="place" subtype="city">Jacksonville</name>, <name type="place" subtype="state">Florida</name>, a graduate of <name type="organization">Florida Normal Institute</name> and holds the degree<lb/>
            <hi rend="center">of doctor of humanity</hi><lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent"><name type="person">Miss White</name> is a pioneer social worker into whose care, <name type="organization">the Federal government</name>, at the close of the last war, entrusted outstanding <name type="organization">Federal</name><lb/>
            projects for social betterment among <name type="person_group">Negroes</name>.
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">Among the institutions which <name type="person">Miss White</name> has promoted and heads are the<name type="organization">Clara White Mission</name> (named for her mother who worked with<lb/>
            her), an agency for the care of orphans and child placement where the needy are fed, clothed, sheltered, and trained for useful employment, and<lb/>
            the <quote>Old Folks' Home,</quote> where fifty aged persons are given residence.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent"><name type="person">Miss White</name> is a member of the <name type="organization">Bethel Baptist Church</name>, a pioneer <name type="organization">Federated Club</name> woman, having served as treasurer of the state federation for<lb/>
         years. She is one of the founders of the <name type="organization">National Association of Colored Women</name> and is a member of the <name type="organization">National Council of Negro women</name>.
         </p>
      </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
