<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="custom.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="m">Manuscript Suspense</title>
            <author>Eartha M.M. White</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription, edition, and encoding</resp>
               <name>Michael "Dean" Rice</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This document forms part of the project "Editing the Eartha M.M. White Archive" at the University of North Florida.</p>            
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <region>Florida</region>                  
                  <settlement>Jacksonville</settlement>                  
                  <repository>University of North Florida, Thomas G. Carpenter Library Special Collections and Archives</repository> 
                  <collection>Eartha M.M. White Collection</collection>
                  <idno>Folder D5, Items 35-48</idno>                  
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc>
                     <p>
                        Documents are all part of a larger manuscript titled "Suspense" by Eartha M.M. White. The documents in this file comprise pages 35-48 of the manuscript. The pages are approximately 8 inches by 11 inches. Most of the pages are in good condition, but a few are in poor condition. The ink has bled on almost every page, but the text is still mostly legible. The text is print.
                     </p>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
     </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <editorialDecl>
           <p>This file was transcribed and encoded according to the editorial criteria of the project "Editing the Eartha M.M. White Archive." Using the various options encoded within &lt;choice&gt; elements, this file enables the viewing of a diplomatic transcription and a regularized reading text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="1" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_35-48_001.jpg"/><!-- Note_1: This file picks up mid-paragraph because it is only a portion of the "Suspense" Manuscript. -->
         <p>
           <choice><orig>35</orig><reg/></choice>guns, soldiers riding up and reading long and important-sounding<lb/>
            proclamations that they couldn't understand, even when blue-clad Negro<lb/>
            soldiers came to the plantations to help them celebrate. To others<lb/>
            emancipation meant guarded whisperings, then a long wait for darkness<lb/>
            so that they could slip away from the masters from whim they still<lb/>
            expected harshness.<lb/>
         </p>
         <lb/>
         <p>
            <hi rend="indent">As in other states, many refused to leave their plantations. In</hi><lb/>
            <name type="place">Duval</name>, <name type="place">St. Johns</name>, <name type="place">Jefferson</name>, and some other counties many of the<lb/>
            slaves remained on the plantations where their descendants may be<lb/>
            found today under a sharecropping arrangement; others were given tracts<lb/>
            of land for their own use.<lb/>
         </p>     
         <lb/>
         <p>
            <hi rend="indent">Many left immediately for the cities. In <name type="place">Jacksonville</name>, where a</hi><lb/>
            number of Northern soldiers were quartered, temporary houses had to<lb/>
            be provided for hundreds of them. Confusion naturally resulted,<lb/>
            intensified by the Negro's entrance into politics, religion, and other<lb/>
            professional fields. Economic helplessness settled on the Negro's<lb/>
            shoulders for a time.<lb/>
         </p>
         <lb/>
         <p>
            <hi rend="indent"><hi rend="underline">Interviews with Ex-Slaves</hi>. Perhaps no form of social life has</hi><lb/>
            been more violently defended and condemned than slavery. To some,<lb/>
            especially when viewed through the softening haze of time, the insti<lb break="no"/>
            tution of slavery seems like paradise on earth; to others it is the<lb/>
            opposite. What did the slaves themselves think of the system? Field<lb/>
            workers of the Florida Writers' Project interviewed more than a score<lb/>
            of ex-slaves and asked them to tell what they remembered. The subjects<lb/>
            of both the following interviews were women, whether because women live<lb/>
            longer or are better talkers than men it would be hard to say.<lb/>
         </p>
         <pb n="2" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_35-48_002.jpg"/>
         <p>
            <choice><orig>36</orig><reg/></choice>
            <hi rend="indent"><hi rend="underline"><name type="person">Margarett Mickerson</name></hi>. <name type="person">Margarett Mickerson</name> was born to </hi><name type="person">William<lb/>
            A. Carr</name> on his plantation near <name type="place">Lake Jackson, Leon County</name>, many years<lb/>
            ago. She now lives in <name type="place">Jacksonville</name> with her daughter.<lb/>
         </p>   
         <lb/>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent"><name type="person">Mr. Kilgo</name> wuz de fust overseer I member; I wuz big enuf to tote</hi><lb/>
               meat an stuff fum de smokehouse to de kitchen an to tote water in an<lb/>
               git wood fur granny to cook de dinner an fur de sucklers who nu'sed<lb/>
               de babies, an I ca'ied dinners back to de hans.<lb/> 
            </quote> 
         </p>
         <lb/>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">On dis plantation was bout a hunnert haid. We done de cookin</hi><lb/>
               in de fiahplace in iron pots, an de meals wuz plenty uf peas, greens,<lb/>
               cornbread, burn co'n fur coffee. Sometime de marster bot coffee fur<lb/>
               us; we got water fum de open well. Jes fore de big gun fiahed dey<lb/>
               fetched my pa fum de bay whar he wuz makin salt; he done hear dem<lb/>   
               say de Yankees is comin an' he shure wuz glad.<lb/> 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <lb/>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">We done had rice an cotton an co'n an taters what got to be</hi><lb/>
               tended, an cowhides to be tanned an thread to be spinned. They done<lb/>
               made de thread into ropes for plow lines.<lb/> 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <lb/>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent"><name type="person">Ole Marse Carr</name> done feed us, but he didn care what an whar, jes</hi> <lb/> 
               so you made money, an when you made five an six bales o cotton he<lb/>
               say you ain done nothin'.<lb/> 
            </quote>
         </p>
         <lb/>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">When de big gun fiahed on a Sat'day me an <name type="person">Cave</name> an <name type="person">Minnie Howard</name></hi><lb/>
               wuz settin up co'n fur de plowers to come long an put dirt to em;<lb/>
               <name type="person">Carr</name> he read de free papers to us on Sunday, an de co'n an cotton<lb/>
            
         
         <pb n="3" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_35-48_003.jpg"/>
         
            <choice><orig>37</orig><reg/></choice>
               dey had to be tended to. <name type="person">Marse Carr</name> he done tole us he gwine gi us<lb/> 
              de net proceeds</quote>—here she chuckles—<quote>what turn out to be de co'n<lb/>
                 an cotton stalks. Den he ask dem whut would stay wid him to step off<lb/>
                 on de right, an dem dat wuz leavin to step off on de lef.<lb/> 
              </quote> 
         </p>
         <lb/>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">My pa made soap fum ashes when he clean de new groun; he done</hi><lb/>
               take a hopper to put de ashes in, made a li'le stool side de house,<lb/>
               put de ashes in an po'red water on it to drip. Den at night when he<lb/>
               git off fum work he done put in de grease an make de soap. I done<lb/>
               make it myself sometime, an I makes it now.<lb/> 
            </quote> 
         </p>
         <lb/>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">My step-pa useter make shoes fum cowhides fur de farm han's on</hi><lb/>
               de plantation an fur ev'y buddy cep ole Marse an his fambly; deys wuz<lb/>
               diffunt, fine.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <lb/>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">My gramma <name type="person">Phoebe Austin</name>—my mother wuz name <name type="person">Rachel Jackson</name> an </hi><lb/>
               my pa wuz name <name type="person">Edmun' Jackson</name>; my mother an uncle <name type ="person">Robert</name> an <name type="person">Joe</name> wuz<lb/>
               stole fum <name type="place">Virginny</name> an fetched here. I don know no niggers dat listed<lb/>
               in de War. I don member much about de War, only when dey started<lb/>
               talking bout drillin men; <name type="person">Joe Sanders</name> wuz a Lootenen. <name type="person">Marse Carr's</name> sons, <name type="person">Tom</name> an <name type="person">Willie</name> went to de War.<lb/>
               </quote>
         </p>
         <lb/>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">We didn had no doctors, only de grannies; we mostly used hippecat</hi><lb/>
               (ipecac) fur medicine.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <lb/>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">Lak I done tole you, <name type="person">Kilgo</name> wuz de fus overseer I ricollec, den</hi><lb/>
               <name type="person">Sanders</name> wuz nex, an <name type="person">Joe Sanders</name> atter him; <name type="person">John C. Heywood</name> came in<lb/>
            
         
         <pb n="4" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_35-48_004.jpg"/>
         
            <choice><orig>38</orig><reg/></choice>
               atter <name type="person">Sanders</name>, an when de big gun fiahed <name type="person">ole man Brockington</name> wuz dere.<lb/>
        I never saw a nigger sol but dey ca'ied em fum our house an I never<lb/>
               seen em no mo.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <lb/>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">We had church wid de white preachers an dey tole us to mine our</hi><lb/>
               masters and missus an we would be saved. Dey don never tole us nothin<lb/>
               buot <name type="person">Jesus</name>.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <lb/>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">When de big gun fiahed <name type="person">Ole Man Carr</name> had six sacks uf Confederate</hi><lb/>
               money whut he wuz ca'ing wid him to <name type="place">Athens, Georgia</name>, an all de time<lb/>
               if any uf us gals whar he wuz done ax him, <name type="person">Marse</name>, please gi us some<lb/>
               money</quote>—here she raised her voice to a high, pitiful tone—<quote>he say I<lb/>
                  aint got a cent, an right den he would have a chis so full it would<lb/>
                  take a whole passle uv slaves to move it. He had plenty co'n, taters,<lb/>
                  pumpkins, hogs, cows, everything, but he didn gi us nothing but strong<lb/>
                  plain close and plenty to eat; we slep in ole common beds an my pa<lb/>
                  made up li'le cribs an put hay in dem fur de chillan.<lb/>
               </quote>
            </p>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">Now if you wanted to keep in wid <name type="person">Marse Carr</name> don drap you shoes</hi><lb/>
               in de fiel an leave em or he'd beat you. You mus tote you shoes in<lb/>
               de fiel. He'd say, you gun-haided debbil, drappin you shoes an<lb/>
               evything over de field.<lb/>
               </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">Now jes lissen, I wanna tell you all I kin, but I wants to tell<lb/></hi>
               it right. Wait now, I don wanna tell no mistakes an I don wanna lie<lb/>
               on nobody. I ain mad now an I know taint no use to lie. I'se taking<lb/>
               my time, I done prayed an got all de malice out o my heart an I ain<lb/>
            
         <pb n="5" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_35-48_005.jpg"/>
         
            <choice><orig>39</orig><reg/></choice>
               gwine tell no lie fer un, an I ain gwine tell no lie on um. I ain<lb/>
               never seed no slaves sole by <name type="person">Marse Carr</name>; he wuz allus tellin me he<lb/>
               wuz gwine sell me but he never did, he sole my pa's fust wife, though.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
         <quote><hi rend="indent">Dere wuz <name type="person">Uncle George Bull</name>, he could read an write. Chile, de</hi><lb/>
            white folks didn lak no nigger whut could read an write. <name type="person">Carr's</name><lb/>
            wife, <name type="person">Miss Jane</name> useter teach us Sunday school but she didn low us<lb/>
            to tech a book wid us hans. So dey useter jes take <name type="person">Uncle George Bull</name><lb/>
            an beat him fur nuthin; dey would beat him an take hime to de lake an<lb/>
            put him on a log an shuv him in de lake, but he allus swim out. When<lb/>
            dey didn do dat dey would beat him tel de blood run outen him an den<lb/>
            trow him in de ditch in de fiel an kivver him up wid dirt, haid an<lb/>
            yeres, an den stick a stick up at his haid. I wuz a water toter<lb/>
            an done stood an seen um do him dat a way more'n once, an I done stood<lb/>
            an looked at um tel dey went way to de udder rows an den I grabbed de<lb/>
            dirt offen him an he'd bresh de dirt off an say t'ank-you, git his<lb/>
            hoe an go on back to work. Dey beat him lak dat an he didn do a t'ing to git dat sort of treatmen.<lb/>
         </quote>
      </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">Some uv de slaves run away, lots uv em. Some done got caught</hi><lb/>
               an when dey ketched em dey put bells on em; fust dey would put a<lb/>
               iron ban aroun dey neck an anudder one aroun dey wais an rivet em<lb/>
               together down de back; de bell would hang around de ban around dey<lb/>
               neck an it would ring when de slave walked an den dey wouldn git away.<lb/>
               Some uv em wore dese bells three an four month, an when dey time wuz<lb/>
               up dey would take em offn em. <name type="person">Jake Overstreet</name>, <name type="person">George Bull</name>, <name type="person">John Green</name>,<lb/>
               <pb n="6" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_35-48_006.jpg"/>
               
               <choice><orig>40</orig><reg/></choice><name type="person">Ruben Golder</name>, <name type="person">Jim Bradley</name> an a host uv others wore dem bells. Dis<lb/>
               is whut I know, not whut someboddy else say. I done see dis mysel.<lb/>
               En missus, when de big gun fiahed, de runaway slaves comed out de<lb/>
               woods fum all d'rections. We wuz in de fiel when it fiahed, but I<lb/>
               members dey wuz all glad.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">Atter de war, we work but we got pay fur it.</hi><lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent"><name type="person">Ole man Pierce</name> an some others would call some kine uv a perlitical</hi><lb/>
               meetin, but I couldn never understan whut dey wuz talkin bout. We<lb/>
               didn had no kine uv schools an all I knows bout dem is I sent my<lb/>
               chillens in <name type="place">Leon</name> an <name type="place">Gadsden County</name>.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="indent"><hi rend="underline"><name type="person">Mama Duck</name></hi></hi>. <quote><hi rend="indent">Who is the oldest settler, whits or colored, that</hi><lb/> 
              you know of in <name type="place">Tampa</name></quote> <quote>See <name type="person">Mama Duck</name>,</quote> the grinning elevator boy<lb/>
            told us, <quote>she bout a hunnert year old.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="indent">So down into the scrub we went and found the old woman hustling</hi><lb/>
            about from washpot to pump. <quote>I'se mighty busy now, cookin breakfas,</quote><lb/>
            she said, <quote>but ef you come back in bout a hour I'll tell you what I<lb/>
            kin bout ole times in <name type="place">Tampa</name>.<lb/>
            </quote> 
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="indent">Her dust-covered dog met us with elaborate demonstrations of</hi><lb/>
            welcome on the return visit.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">Owan away f'm here, Spot; dat Comman aint gwine feed you nuthin.</hi><lb/>
               You keep yo dirty paws offen his close.<lb/>
               </quote>
         </p>
         <pb n="7" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_35-48_007.jpg"/>
         <p>
            <choice><orig>41</orig><reg/></choice>
         <hi rend="indent"><name type="person">Mama Duck</name> sat down on a rickety box, motioning us to another on</hi><lb/>
            the shaky old porch. <quote>Take care you don fall thoo dat ol flo,</quote> she<lb/>
            cautioned. <quote>Hit bout ready to go to pieces, but I'se way behin on<lb/>
               de rent, so I caint ask em to have hit fixed.</quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">I see you have no glass in the windows—doesn't it get you wet when it rains?</hi><lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">Not me, cause I gits ovah on de udder side o de room when hit</hi><lb/>
               rains. Didn't have no do, neither, when I moved in. Young folks<lb/>
               round here used to use hit fo a co't house afo I come.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">A what?</hi>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">Court house. Kep a-comin atter I dine move in, an I had to shoo</hi><lb/>
               em away. Dat young rascal comin yonda, he one of em. I claiah to<lb/>
               goodness...</quote> and <name type="person">Mama Duck</name> raised her voice for the trespasser's<lb/>
            benefit, <quote>I wisht I had me a fence to keep folks outa my yahd.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">Qau-a-ck, quack, quack,</hi></quote> the dressed-up young Negro mocked, as<lb/>
            he passed on, grinning.
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               Dat don worry me none; I don let nutin worry me—worry makes<lb/>
               folks gray-haided,</quote> the old woman said, as she scratched her thinly-<lb/>
            covered head. Three braids, about the length and thickness of an<lb/>
            eyebrow stuck out at odd angles, and there were not more than a dozen<lb/>
            gray hairs streaking the rusty black.<lb/>
         </p>
         <pb n="8" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_35-48_008.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <choice><orig>42</orig><reg/></choice>
               <quote><hi rend="indent">I sho had plenty chance to worry effen I wanted to,</hi></quote><hi rend="indent"> she mused,</hi><lb/>
               as she sipped ice water from a fruit jar foul with dirty fingermarks.<lb/>
               <quote>Relief folks got me on de black list. Dey give rations to young<lb/>
                  folks what's wukkin and don give me narry a mouthful.<lb/>
               </quote>
            </p>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">How's that?</hi>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">Well, in de fust place, dey wanted me to go to de po house. I</hi><lb/>
               wanted to take mah trunk long, an dey wouldn let me. I got some t'ings<lb/>
               in dere I be'n havin nigh onto a hunnert year. Got my ol blue-back<lb/>
               Webster, onlies book I evah had, scusin mah Bible. T'ink I wanna throw<lb/>
               dat stuff away? No-o suh!</quote> <name type="person">Mama Duck</name> pushed the dog away from a<lb/>
            cracked pitcher on the floor and refilled her fruit jar. <quote>So dey<lb/>
               black-list me, cause I won kiss dey feets. I aint kissin nobody's<lb/>
               feets—wouldn't kiss my own mammy's.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">Well, we'd all do lots of things for our mothers that we wouldn't</hi><lb/>
            do for anyone else.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">Mebbe</hi> you would, but not me. My mammay put me in a hickry basket<lb/>
               when I was a day an a half ole with nuttin on but my belly ban an a<lb/>
               di'per. Took me down in de cotton patch an sot de basket on a stump<lb/>
               in de bilin sun.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">What in the world did she do that for?</hi>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">Cause I was black. All de othah young uns was bright. My</hi><lb/>
               granmammy done hear me bawlin an go fetch me to my mammy's house.
               </quote>
         </p>
         <pb n="9" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_35-48_009.jpg"/>
         <p>
            <choice><orig>43</orig><reg/></choice>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">‘Dat you, Mammy?’ she say, sweet as pie, when granmammy poun</hi><lb/>
               on de do.</quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">‘Don you nevah call me Mammy no mo,’ granmammy say. ‘Any wo</hi><lb break="no"/>
               man what'd leave a po li'le mite lak dis to perish to death aint<lb/>
               fitten to be no datter o mine.’
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">So granmammy tuk me to raise. I aint nevah seen my mammy</hi><lb/>
               sence, an I nevah want to.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">What did your father think of the way she treated you?</hi><lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">Nevah knew who mah daddy was, an I reckon she didn neither.</hi><lb/>
               I was bawned at <name type="place">Richard, Virginia</name>; mah sister an brother be'n dead<lb/>
               too many year to count—I de las o de fam'ly.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">Do you remember anything about the War between the States?</hi><lb/></quote>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">What dat?</hi></quote><lb/>
            <quote><hi rend="indent"></hi><name type="event">The Civil War</name>, when they set the slaves free.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">Oh, de fust war, you mean. I reckon I does—had three childen,</hi><lb/>
               boys, bawned befo de war. Mah fust mastah didn make us wuk none<lb/>
               when we was chillens. All I done was play. When I was ole enough<lb/>
               to wuk, dey tuk us to <name type="place">Pelman, Georgia</name>. I nevah wukked in de fiel's,<lb/>
               not den, dey allus let me nuss de chillens. Den I got married in<lb/>
               granmammy's kitchen an went to us own log house. By an by mah mastah<lb/>
               sole me an mah baby to de man what had de plantation nex to ours—<lb/>
               his name was <name type="person">John Lee</name>. He was good to me, an let me see mah chillens.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <pb n="10" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_35-48_010.jpg"/>
         <p>
            <choice><orig>44</orig><reg/></choice>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">How would he punish his pets?</hi></quote><lb/>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">Sometimes he jes bop em 'erost de yere wid a battlin stick..</hi></quote><lb/>
            <quote><hi rend="indent">A what?</hi></quote><lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <quote>
                  <hi rend="indent">Battlin stick, lak dis. You don know what a battlin stick is?</hi><lb/>
                  Well, dis yere one. Use hit for washin close. You lif em outa de<lb/>
                  wash pot wid de battlin stick, den you lay em on de battlin block, dis<lb/>
                  yere stump. Den you beat de dirt out wid de battlin stick.<lb/>
               </quote>
            </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">Great guns, that stick would knock a horse down!</hi><lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">Nossuh, wasn't nigh as bad as some o de othahs got. He had pets</hi><lb/>
               mongst de mens, too, but dey got hit a li'le wusser dan de wimmons.<lb/>
               Effen dey wasn't too mean, he jes strap em 'crost de sharp side of a<lb/>
               bar'l an give em a few right smaht licks wid a bull whip.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">H'm—they did get off light, didn't they; and what would he do</hi><lb/>
               to the bad ones?<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">Well, sometimes dey try to run away; den he mek em cross de</hi><lb/>
               han's, lak dis. Den he tie a rope roun dey wrists an thow hit ovah<lb/>
               a tree limb. Den he pull em up so dey toes jes touch de groun an<lb/>
               smack em on de back an rump wid a heavy wooden paddle, fixed ful o<lb/>
               holes. Know what dem holes was fur? Ev'y hole mak a blister. Den<lb/>
               he mak em lay down on de groun whilst he bus all dem blisters wid a<lb/>
               rawhide whip.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">I should think that would kill any man.</hi><lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <pb n="11" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_35-48_011.jpg"/>
         <p>
            <choice><orig>45</orig><reg/></choice>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">Nevah heard o nobody dyin f'm gittin a beatin. Some couldn wuk</hi><lb/>
               for a day or two. Sometimes dey thow salt brine on dey backs, or<lb/>
               smear on turpentine to make it git well quicker.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">Well, I suppose you're glad that those days are over.</hi><lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">Not me. I was aheap bettah off den as I is now. Allus had</hi><lb/>
                  sumpin to eat an a place to stay. No sech t'ing as gittin on a black<lb/>
                  list. Mighty hard on a pusson ol as me not to git no rations an not<lb/>
                  have no reg'lar job.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">How old are you?</hi><lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">I don know, 'sackly. Mebbe—wait a minute, I didn show you my</hi><lb/>
                  pitcher what wuz in de paper, did I? I caint read, but somebody say<lb/>
                  dey put how ol I is under mah pitcher in dat paper.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="indent"><name type="person">Mama Duck</name> rummaged through a cigar box and brought out a page of</hi><lb/>
               a <name type="place">Pittsburg</name> newspaper, dated a year ago. It was so badly worn that<lb/>
               it was almost illegible, but it showed a picture of the old woman and<lb/>
               below it was given her age, 109.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="indent">In answer to the question regarding the length of her residence</hi><lb/>
            in <name type="place">Tampa</name> she said that she didn't remember. <quote>Come here when dey was<lb/>
               only one sto,</quote> she mused. <quote>Hit b'long to <name type="person">Ol Man Mugge</name>. Dey raised<lb/>
                  cotton where <name type="place">Plant City</name> is now.<lb/> I picked some cotton dere, den I<lb/>
                  come to <name type="person">Tampa</name> an atter a while I got a job nussin <name type="person">Mister Perry Wall</name>'s<lb/>
                  chillen. Cullud folks jes mek out de bes dey could. Some of em lived<lb/>
                  in tents tell dey could cut logs an build houses wid sticks an dirt<lb/>
                  chimbleys.<lb/>
               </quote>
         </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_35-48_012.jpg"/>
            <p>
               <choice><orig>46</orig><reg/></choice>
               <hi rend="indent">Judging only by the appearance of this wiry old woman, it is</hi><lb/>
               hard to realize that <name type="person">John Quincy Adams</name> was serving as the country's sixth<lb/>
               president when <name type="person">Kate Bennett</name> left her unwanted black baby in a <name type="place">Virginia</name><lb/>
               cotton patch. An interesting study, this patient old crone resigned<lb/>
               to unpleasant circumstances over which she has no control, curbing<lb/>
               her temper in the face of petty annoyances, sitting in a dusty alley<lb/>
               with her cur dog, as she stolidly waits for the last curtain to fall<lb/>
               on her long drama of life.<lb/>
      </p>
         <p>
            <hi rend="indent"><hi rend="underline">A Slaveholder Speaks</hi>. Mention has previously been made of a</hi><lb/>
            slaveholder by no means unfavorably disposed towards the Negroes,<lb/>
            since he married a Negro woman and left her his property. Perhaps<lb/>
            his opinion of slavery is as impartial as any we can have, and it has<lb/>
            the merit of being practical and not theoretical. The following ex<lb break="no"/>
            cerpt is from <title level="m">the Patriarchal System of Society</title>, by <name type="person">Zephaniah Kingsley</name>,<lb/>
            a book which ran through four editions.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p>
            <quote>
               <hi rend="indent">About 25 years ago, I settled a plantation of<name type="place">St. Johns River</name></hi>,<lb/>
            in <name type="place">Florida</name> with about 50 new African Negroes, many of whom I brought<lb/>
            from the coast myself. They were mostly fine young men and women, and<lb/>
               nearly in equal numbers. I never interfered with their connubial<lb/>
               concerns, nor domestic affairs, but let them regulate these after<lb/>
               their own manner. I taught them nothing but what was useful, and<lb/>
               what I thought would add to their physical and moral happiness. I<lb/>
               encouraged as much as possible dancing, merriment and dress, for which<lb/>
               Saturday afternoon and night, and Sunday morning were dedicated; and,<lb/>
               <pb n="13" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_35-48_013.jpg"/>
                  <choice><orig>47</orig><reg/></choice>
               after allowance, their time was usually employed in hoeing their<lb/>
               corn, and getting a supply of fish for the week. Both men and women<lb/>
               were very industrious. Many of them made 20 bushels of corn to sell,<lb/>
               and they vied with each other in dress and dancing, and as to whose<lb/>
               woman was the finest and prettiest. They were perfectly honest and<lb/>
               obedient, and appeared quite happy, having no fear but that of offend<lb break="no"/>
               ing me; and I hardly ever had occasion to apply other correction than<lb/>
               shaming them. If I exceeded this, the punishment was quite light,<lb/>
               for they hardly ever failed in doing their work well. My object was<lb/>
               to excite their ambition and attachment by kindness; not to depress<lb/>
               their spirits by fear and punishment. I never allowed them to visit,<lb/>
               for fear of bad example, but encouraged the decent neighboring people<lb/>
               to participate in their weekly festivity, for which they always pro<lb break="no"/>
               vided an ample entertainment themselves, as they had an abundance of<lb/>
               hogs, fowls, corn, and all kinds of vegetables and fruit. They had<lb/>
               nothing to conceal from me, and I had no suspicion of any crime in<lb/>
               them to guard against. Perfect confidence, friendship, and good<lb/>
               understanding reigned between us: they increased rapidly. After a<lb/>
               few years, this pleasant and profitable state of harmony was in<lb break="no"/>
               terrupted by the revolution of 1812. A war party of Seminole Indians<lb/>
               attacked the plantation in my absence; caught, bound, and carried off,<lb/>
               or killed 40 of them, whose reluctance in going with the invaders may<lb/>
               be imagined from the following circumstance. The wife of a young<lb/>
               man they had tied and were driving off, that her husband, who was too<lb/>
               strong to be handled and who had his young child in his arms, might<lb/>
               <pb n="14" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_35-48_014.jpg"/>
               <choice><orig>48</orig><reg/></choice>
               follow; but this he absolutely refused, handing over the child to his<lb/>
               wife, and saying that she knew best how to take care of it, but that<lb/>
               his master should never say that he was a runaway negro; upon which<lb/>
               the Indian shot him, and he died next day.<lb/>
            </quote>
         </p>
         
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
