<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="custom.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Suspense</title>
            <author>Unknown</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription, edition, and encoding</resp>
               <name>Lauren Kelley Winters</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p rend="indent">This document forms part of the project "Editing the Eartha M.M. White Archive" at the University of North Florida.</p>            
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <region>Florida</region>                  
                  <settlement>Jacksonville</settlement>                  
                  <repository>University of North Florida, Thomas G. Carpenter Library Special Collections and Archives</repository> 
                  <collection>Eartha M.M. White Collection</collection>
                  <idno>Folder D5, Item 1687</idno>                  
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc>
                     <p rend="indent">This document dated June 20, </p>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
     </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <editorialDecl>
           <p rend="indent">This file was transcribed and encoded according to the editorial criteria of the project "Editing the Eartha M.M. White Archive." Using the various options encoded within &lt;choice&gt; elements, this file enables the viewing of a diplomatic transcription and a regularized reading text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="1" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_001.jpg"/>
         <div>
            <note place="marginTop">Suspense- Negro Book June  <supplied reason="text faded" cert="medium">20, 1941</supplied> </note>
            <head><label rend="case(allcaps)">Chapter I: Early History</label></head>
            <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline">The First Negroes in <name type="place">Florida</name>,</hi>Perhaps the earliest mention of<lb/>
            a Negro in <name type="place">Florida</name> occurs in the account of the expedition of <name type="person">Narvaes</name><lb/>
            in <date when="1528">1528</date>. It will be recalled that after the ruin of that expedition<lb/>
            <name type="person">Cabeza de Vaca</name> and three companies reached <name type="nation">Mexico</name> after almost six<lb/>
            years of incredible suffering. According to <name type="person">De Vaca</name>'s account, one<lb/>
            of his companions was <name type="person">Esteban</name>, a blackamoor from <name type="place">Asomeur</name> on the west<lb/>
            coast of <name type="nation">Morocco</name>, who was the slave of <name type="person">Dorantes</name>, capatain of infantry<lb/>
            in <name type="person">Narvaes</name>' army.<lb/>
         </p>
            <p rend="indent">
            This same Negro was the guide of <name type="person">Fray Marcos de Nisa</name> in <date when="1539">1539</date>, and<lb/>
            was sent ahead of the Corenado expedition to report the character of<lb/>
            the country. <name type="person">Esteban</name>'s experience with Indians and his natural dramatic<lb/>
            instinct led him to plan an impressive entrance into the new regions,<lb/>
            but he knew <name type="person">Fray Marcos</name> would not approve. Accordingly, he persuaded<lb/>
            the priest to allow him to travel two days in advance, and a strange<lb/>
            procession went forward: <name type="person">Esteban</name>, borne like Indian royalty on a cano<lb break="no"/>
            pied seat and accompanied by hundreds of male and female attendants,<lb/>
            while after him plodded <name type="person">Fray Marcos</name>, afoot, with only a small native<lb/>
            guard. All went well until <name type="person">Esteban</name> reached the <name type="place">country of the Yunis</name>,<lb/>
            who refused to be awed and fell upon him and killed him. <name type="person">Fray Marcos</name><lb/>
            escaped a similar fate by presenting trinkets to the Indians.<lb/>
             </p>
            <p rend="indent">
            With slavery a widespread institution in <name type="place">Europe</name>, it was natural<lb/>
            that slaves were used in developing <name type="place">the New World</name>. There were some<lb/>
               Negro slaves with <name type="person">John Harkins</name> when he stopped at <name type="place">Fort Caroline<location><geo>30.385350 -81.497227</geo></location></name> on the<lb/>
            <pb n="2" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_002.jpg"/> 
               <name type="place">St. Johns River<location><geo>30.401351 -81.400876</geo></location></name> in <date when="1565">1565</date>. He had sold most of his slaves to <name type="person_group">Spaniards</name><lb/>
            in the <name type="place">West Indies</name>, but one Negro was reported lost on the shore in<lb/>
               front of <name type="place">Fort Caroline<location><geo>30.385350 -81.497227</geo></location></name>, and was believed to have been eaten by an al<lb break="no"/>
            ligator. It is not improbable, however, that he escaped and sought<lb/>
            refuge among the Indians, as so many of his race did later.<lb/>
         </p>
            <p rend="indent">
            There were Negro slaves in <name type="place">St. Augustine</name>, probably from the very<lb/>
            first, but their number was negligible. Negro slaves of the <name type="person"><name type="person_group">Spanish</name><lb/>
               King</name> were sent to <name type="place">Florida</name> in <date when="1581">1581</date>, and a small party of them were<lb/>
            employed for two years in making wooden platforms for the artillery of<lb/>
            the <name type="place">old fort at St. Augustine</name>. There is also a record of a Negro slave<lb/>
            at the <name type="place">St. Augustine friary</name> in <date when="1469">1569</date>. In <date when="1594">1594</date> the <name type="person">Governor of <name type="place">Florida</name></name><lb/>
            asked the <name type="person">Governor of <name type="nation">Cuba</name></name> for a number of soldiers and a "few slaves."<lb/>
            In the first hospital in the <name type="nation">United States</name>, built at <name type="place">St. Augustine</name> in<lb/>
            <date when="1597">1597</date>, a Negroess in the royal service tended "soldiers, Indian, and<lb/>
            Negroes." In <date when="1603">1603</date> there were 32 Negro slaves in <name type="place">St. Augustine</name>, five<lb/>
            of whom were women. It is likely that these Negro slaves were servants,<lb/>
            as the <name type="person_group">Spanish</name> enslaved Indians for hard labor.<lb/>
         </p>
            <p rend="indent">
            However, the Indians reacted so unsatisfactorily to strenuous manual<lb/>
            labor that the arrival of Negro slaves for field work was hailed with<lb/>
            joy. A shout went up as the ship of <name type="person">Don Juan de Aila</name> came to another in<lb/>
            the <name type="place">harbor of St. Agustine</name> in <date when="1687">1687</date>, a shout that was the beginning of<lb/>
            a celebration lasting all day. For, on the ship of the Don, in addition<lb/>
            to the usual cargo, was a black slave, the one survivor of the 12 that<lb/>
            the <name type="person_group">Spaniard</name> had put on board.<lb/>
         </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_003.jpg"/>
            <p rend="indent">
            To the <name type="person_group">Spanish</name> colonists of new <name type="place">Florida</name> the slave came to mean<lb/>
            food--someone to raise crops on the farms near <name type="place">St. Augustine</name>. The<lb/>
            new slave had companions because the <name type="person_group">Spaniards</name> were strict; in<lb/>
            addition to other qualifications, a slave was required to become a<lb/>
            Catholic before being brought into <name type="place">Florida</name>.<lb/>
         </p>
            <p rend="indent">
            The slave of <name type="person">Don Juan</name> was not long to remain alone; in the years<lb/>
            that immediately followed he was joined, at <name type="place">St. Augustine</name> and other<lb/>
            parts of the region, by numbers of other Negroes who sought the col<lb break="no"/>
            onists of the <name type="place">Carolinas</name>.<lb/>
         </p>
            <p rend="indent">
            It was during this period of the first <name type="person_group">Spanish</name> occupation of<lb/>
            <name type="place">Florida</name> that the connection between the Negro and the Indian first<lb/>
            occurred. Indians were if the <name type="person_group">Creek</name> and <name type="person_group">Yamaneo</name> tribes, who occupied<lb/>
            a wide territory in what was later to be <name type="place">Georgia</name>. Both Indians and<lb/>
            Negroes frequently escaped from their masters in <name type="place">Carolina</name>, and made<lb/>
            their way southward to the <name type="person_group">Spanish</name> territory of <name type="place">Florida</name>. Here the<lb/>
            <name type="person_group">Spaniards</name> erected a fort for the refugees, a few miles north of their<lb/>
               own <name type="place">San Marcos</name>. This fort, called <name type="place">Fort Moosa<location><geo>29.927681 -81.325081</geo></location></name>,was built between <date when="1687">1687</date><lb/>
            and <date when="1695">1695</date>; it consisted of a large square with breastwork and four<lb/>
            bastions. In and near this fort a larger group of Negroes lived in<lb/>
            comparative freedom.<lb/>     
         </p>
            <p rend="indent">
            The constant escape of Negro and Indian slaves from <name type="place">Carolina</name> to<lb/>
            <name type="place">Florida</name> contributed to the creation of the <name type="place">Georgia</name> colony. In <name type="place">Georgia</name>,<lb/>
            <pb n="4" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_004.jpg"/>
           ownership of slaves was at first forbidden, as it was believed that<lb/>
            a free state between <name type="place">Florida</name> and <name type="place">Carolina</name> would greatly reduce the<lb/>
            number of escapes. After eight years, the need for Negro labor ended<lb/>
            the free status of <name type="place">Georgia</name>.<lb/>
         </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               By <date when="1740-06">June of 1740</date>, the number of Negroes occupying <name type="place">Fort Moosa<location><geo>29.927681 -81.325081</geo></location></name> had<lb/>
            become a factor in the threatening hostilities between the <name type="person_group">Spaniards</name><lb/>
            and <name type="person">Governor James Oglethorpe of <name type="place">Georgia</name></name>. Learning that the <name type="person_group">English</name>man<lb/>
            planned an attack, the <name type="person_group">Spanish</name> governor, <name type="person">Montiano</name>, strengthened both<lb/>
               forts <name type="place">Moosa<location><geo>29.927681 -81.325081</geo></location></name> and <name type="place">San Marcos<location><geo>29.897908 -81.311529</geo></location></name>. A band of 80 <name type="person_group">Scotch Highlnders</name>, however,<lb/>
               captured <name type="place">Fort Moosa<location><geo>29.927681 -81.325081</geo></location></name> in the early days of the <name type="person">Oglethorpe</name> invasion of<lb/>
            <name type="place">St. Augustine</name>, and it was later retaken only after several hundred<lb/>
            <name type="person_group">Spaniards</name> and Negroes had been hurled against it. In this engagement,<lb/>
            the <name type="person_group">English</name> leader, <name type="person">Colonel Palmer</name>, was killed, and many of his men<lb/>
            were captured and imprisoned in the <name type="place">St. Augustine</name> fort.<lb/>
         </p>
            <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline">The <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> Increases.</hi> The infiltration of <name type="place">Georgia</name> Indians into<lb/>
            <name type="place">Florida</name> greatly increased about <date when="1750">1750</date> when a chieftain of the <name type="person_group">Creek</name> in<lb/>
            <name type="place">Georgia</name>, <name type="person">Seacoffee</name>, left the <name type="person_group">Creek</name> tribes and moved into <name type="place">Florida</name> with<lb/>
            a large following. They mingled with both Negroes and the <name type="person_group">Miccosukee</name><lb/>
            Indians who had preceded tham, and enjoyed many of the privileges of<lb/>
            free <name type="person_group">Spanish</name> citizenship. Gradually the Indian tribes in <name type="place">Florida</name><lb/>
            became known as <name type="person_group">Seminole</name>, meaning separatists or runaways.<lb/>
         </p>
            <p rend="indent">
            When <name type="place">Georgia</name> became a slave-holding province, the number of Indians<lb/>
            and Negro runaways in <name type="place">Florida</name> increased rapidly, to the extent, finally,<lb/>
            <pb n="5" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_005.jpg"/>
            that in <date when="1776">1776</date> the Council for Safety of <name type="place">Georgia</name> requested from Congress<lb/>
            a large force of troops "to prevent their slaves from deserting their<lb/>
            Masters."<lb/>
         </p>
            <p rend="indent">
            About this date it became known that Indians and Negro runaways<lb/>
            had settled in numbers around the <name type="place">Suwannee</name> and <name type="place">Apalachicola</name> Rivers, in<lb/>
            addition to the settlements they already had in eastern and central<lb/>
            <name type="place">Florida</name>. This brief prosperity that the Negroes and <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> enjoyed--<lb/>
            the last in their history--was made possible by the war between <name type="nation">England</name><lb/>
            and the <name type="nation">American colonies</name>, the largely unexplored condition of <name type="place">Florida</name><lb/>
            as a whole, and the fact that within the <name type="place">Carolina</name>, <name type="place">North Georgia</name>, and<lb/>
            <name type="place">Florida</name> boundaries there were still savage tribes of <name type="person_group">>Creek</name> Indians to<lb/>
            be encountered.<lb/>
         </p>
            <p rend="indent">
            The first serious threat to this breathing-spell came in <date when="1783">1783</date>,<lb/>
            when, at the close of the Revolutionary War, the Creek of <name type="place">Georgia</name> made<lb/>
            a treaty with the authorities of the state, in which they promised to<lb/>
            restore all slaves residing among them. While the authenticity of this<lb/>
            treaty was disputed, it was to have a profound effect upon the fate of<lb/>
            the escaped Negroes and <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> in <name type="place">Florida</name>.<lb/>
         </p>
            <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline">The Second <name type="person_group">Spanish Period</name></hi>. The Second <name type="person_group">Spanish</name> period was one of<lb/>-->
            significant developments for Negroes. Although the <name type="person_group">British</name>, departing<lb/>
            from <name type="place">Florida</name> after the <name type="person_group">American</name> Revolution, took their slaves with them<lb/>
            many more were brought in by planters who moved to <name type="place">Florida</name> to take up<lb/>
            <name type="person_group">Spanish</name> grants. These adventurers from the new <name type="nation">United States</name> imported<lb/>
            slaves direct from <name type="place">Africa</name>, a practice forbidden in the <name type="nation">>United States</name><lb/>
            <pb n="6" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_006.jpg"/>
            after 1808, but countenanced in <name type="place">Florida</name> by <name type="person_group">Spanish</name> law. As a result,<lb/>
            slaves were brought to <name type="place">Florida</name> in great numbers. The majority of them<lb/>
            were then smuggled across the <name type="place"><name type="nation">American</name> border</name> into <name type="place">Georgia</name> and other<lb/>
            states. Their value soared as cotton plantation spread over the<lb/>
            lower South.<lb/>
         </p>
            <p rend="indent">
            Toward the Indians and their Negro allies the Spanish governors<lb/>
            were not as liberal as in former years. The <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> had never been<lb/>
            <name type="person_group">Spanish</name> adherents, and the <name type="place">Gerogia</name> Creek Began a series of raids into<lb/>
            <name type="place">Florida</name>, burning villages and taking prisoners.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            The first treaty made under the Constitution of the <name type="nation">United States</name><lb/>
            was in reference to Negroes involved in these border events. In a con<lb break="no"/>
            cession of certain lands to the <name type="place">Georgia</name> <name type="person_group">Creek</name>, a repetition was made of<lb/>
            the stipulation that Negroes were to be surrendered by the Indians.<lb/>
            This provision set the <name type="person_group">Creek</name> to invading <name type="place">Florida</name> so that they might have<lb/>
            Negro captives to surrender. The treaty bore the date of <date when="1790-08-01">August 1, 1790</date>,<lb/>
            and the signature of <name type="person">President George Washington</name>.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            The succeeding quarter of a century witnessed two interesting<lb/>
            developments for the Negroes of <name type="place">West Florida</name> and their Indian allies:<lb/>
            an intensification of the efforts of the officials of slaveholding<lb/>
            <name type="place">Georgia</name> to reclaim the growing number of free Negroes in <name type="place">Florida</name>, and<lb/>
            the tighter cementing of the bonds between Negroes and <name type="person_group">Seminole</name>. The<lb/>
            Indians and Negroes in <date when="1812">1812</date> defeated an army raised by <name type="place">Georgia</name> which had<lb/>
            penetrated about a hundred miles into <name type="place">Florida</name>; they cut it off from its<lb/>
            supplies, and sent it back nearly starved. In <date when="1811">1811</date> the Governor of<lb/>
            <pb n="7" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_007.jpg"/>
            <name type="place">Georgia</name> ordered the formation of an army large enough "to reduce<lb/>
            <name type="place">St. Augustine</name> and punish the Indians."<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            It was not in the <name type="place">East Florida</name> section around <name type="place">St. Augustine</name>,<lb/>
            however, that the Negroes suffered their first major disaster. An<lb/>
            expedition did enter that section of the state during the <name type="place">Republic of<lb/>
               Florida</name> rebellion, but after two years returned to Georgia with little<lb/>
            but casualties to show for its efforts.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            In <date when="1814">1814</date> several <name type="person_group">British</name> vessels assisted the Negroes and <name type="person_group">Seminole</name><lb/>
            in the area around the <name type="place">Apelachicola River</name> to erect a fort, stock it<lb/>
            with ammunition, and mount it with eight guns. This fort was about<lb/>
            thirty miles above the mouth of the river, on its east bank. The fort<lb/>
            was generally called the Negro Fort, but its official name was <name type="place">Fort<lb/>
               Blount</name>. That the Negroes and their <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> friends believed in the <lb/>
            security of the fort seems evident from the fact that many farms and<lb/>
            plantations sprang up in the vicinity; one historian says cultivated<lb/>
            feields extended more than fifty miles along the river. There were<lb/>
            hundreds of Negroes and <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> in the area, and they owned large<lb/>
            herds of cattle and horses.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            On the morning of <date when="1816-05-24">July 24, 1816</date>, the quiet of the fort was shat<lb break="no"/>
            tered by the booming of the two 18-pound guns; <name type="person">General Andrew Jackson</name>, in<lb/>
            charge of the southern forces of the <name type="nation">United States</name> Army, had ordered<lb/>
            <name type="person">Colonel Clinch</name> and <name type="person">Captain Loomis</name> to attack the fort, "blow it up, and<lb/>
            return the niggers to their rightful owners."<lb/>
         </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_008.jpg"/>
         <p rend="indent">
            After four days of attack from both land and water, a heated<lb/>
            cannonball pierced a powder magazine incide the stockade, and all<lb/>
            but 60 of the 334 persons inside the fort were instantly killed. Only<lb/>
            three escaped injury. Two of the survivors, one Indian and one Negro,<lb/>
            were executed as "leaders."<lb/>
         </p>
         </div>
         <pb n="9" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_009.jpg"/>
            <div>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="center"><label rend="case(allcaps)">Chapter II<lb/>
                     <name type="place">Florida</name> Ceded to the <name type="nation">United States</name></label><lb/>
                  </hi>
               </head>
          <p rend="indent">
             On <date when="1821-07-10">July 10, 1821</date>, the Negroes in <name type="place">Florida</name> saw the <name type="person_group">American</name> flag<lb/>
            raised over the Territory. It meant the enslavement of every Negro<lb/>
             who could be captured. Under <name type="person_group">Spanish</name> law a slave could file a petition<lb/>
             for a new master, while under <name type="person_group">American</name> law his testimony was not al<lb break="no"/>
             lowed in court. The <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> also viewed <name type="person_group">Americans</name> with disfavor, hav<lb break="no"/>
             ing fought as <name type="person_group">English</name> allies against them in the Revolution. So the<lb/>
             reaction of the <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> and the Negroes associated with them was to<lb/>
            retire deeper into the fastnesses of the <name type="place">Florida</name> swamps and forests,<lb/>
             and to resist the <name type="person_group">American</name> forces in what were to become famous as the<lb/>
             <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> Wars.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline"><name type="person_group">Seminole</name> Wars</hi>. From the destruction of <name type="place">Fort Blount</name> in <date when="1816">1816</date>, until<lb/>
            <date when="1842">1842</date>, the <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> Wars were waged intermittantly. Actually, there had<lb/>
            been no peace between the <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> and their Negro allies on the one<lb/>
            hand and the <name type="person_group">American</name> forces on the other since the destruction of <name type="place">Fort<lb/>
            Blount</name>. <name type="person">General Jackson</name>, with four thousand regular and volunteer<lb/>
            troops, had already defeated Negroes in several towns around <name type="place">Lake<lb/>
               Miccosukee</name>, the <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> in <name type="place">St. Marks</name> on the <name type="place">Gulf</name>, and combines <name type="person_group">Sem<lb break="no"/>
            inole</name> and Negro forces along the <name type="place">Suwannee</name>. Those who were not killed<lb/>
            or captured fled to the <name type="place">Everglades</name>.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            On <date when="1842-08-14">Auguat 14, 1842</date>, <name type="person">General J.W. Worth</name> issued an official order<lb/>
            that "hostilities with the Indians within these territories have<lb/>
            ceased." The intervening 26 years had seen the question of surrender<lb break="no"/>
            ing the Negroes cause the postponement of peace with the <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> many<lb/>
            <pb n="10" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_010.jpg"/>
            times; had seen the same question become a major issue first among army<lb/>
            officials; then in the houses of Congress, and finally assist in the<lb/>
            unloading of an attorney-general and the discomfiture of presidents <name type="person">Van<lb/>
               Buren</name> and <name type="person">Tayler</name>.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            The campaigne of the <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> Wars made many historic figures<lb/>
            among whites, Negroes and Indians alike. Because of the enslavement of<lb/>
            <name type="person">Morning Dew</name>, his <name type="person_group">Creek</name>-Negro wife, the embittered young warrior <name type="person">Osceola</name><lb/>
            became one of the most feared leaders of the <name type="person_group">Seminole</name>. <name type="person">Coaccochee</name> and<lb/>
            his inseparable friend <name type="person">Louis</name>--a forment Negro slave who led <name type="person">Major Dade</name>'s<lb/>
            army detachment into ambush rather than assist in an attack on the Ne<lb break="no"/>
            groes and <name type="person_group">Seminole</name>--grew so terrible in legend that there was wide<lb break="no"/>
            spread relief when they agreed to depart from <name type="place">Florida</name> to the west.<lb/>
            <name type="person">Micanopy</name>, with his Negro <name type="person">Abraham</name>--who twice interpreted governmental<lb/>
            treaties so well that clauses objectionable to the Indians had to be<lb/>
            removed-- these and many others crosses <name type="place">Florida</name>'s history during the<lb/>
            turbulent years of the <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> Wars. For years after the close of the<lb/>
            <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> War, scattered Indians and their Negroes, usually called Maroons,<lb/>
            were a source of concern to the settlers.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Maroons were those Negroes, living among the <name type="person_group">Seminole</name>, who were<lb/>
            descendants of runaway slaves, and yet had never themselves belonged<lb/>
            to a white man. Proof of their descent usually consisted in demon<lb break="no"/>
            stration of their ability to speak the <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> language. The <name type="nation">United<lb/>
            States</name> Government finally decided that Maroons might emigrate, and<lb/>
            about four hundred of them went west with the <name type="person_group">Seminole</name>.<lb/>
         </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_011.jpg"/>
         <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline">Capture of the Last Indian on <name type="place">Amelia Island<location><geo>30.626669 -81.459823</geo></location></name></hi>. <name type="person">Morris Drummond</name>,<lb/>
            Negro resident of <name type="place">Amelia Island<location><geo>30.626669 -81.459823</geo></location></name> near the northeasten border of <name type="place">Flor<lb break="no"/>
            ida</name>, gave the following account of the capture of the last Indian<lb/>
            there: "You want to hear how dey ketch de las Indian on dis hyear is<lb break="no"/>
            land? My granpaw say dey keep a-noticin someun in de cawn patch--de<lb/>
            cawn was broke off, an trompled. <name type="person">Marse Harrison</name> say, 'someun stealin<lb/>
            my cawn, an I blieve it de Indians.'<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            "Dey notice dat dar ony one set of tranks, but dey know how tricky<lb/>
            dem Indians is. Missis, dey mought be forty or fifty of dem critters,<lb/>
            but dey wouldon lebe but one set of tracks--one ud dem Indians, not<lb/>
            knowin how many dey be. So <name type="person">Marse Harrison</name> plan dat de whole bunch of<lb/>
            buck niggahs surroun dat cawn fiel, an wait. Ifen dey be's a lot of<lb/>
            Indian, we all gwine run; if dey be one or two, we gwine ketch em.<lb/>
            Tareckly dark come outa de woods, widdout no sound come one Indian, an<lb/>
            he warn't too big/ He creep inta de cawn patch an start breakin off de<lb/>
            cawn. Den we all rush im. We ain fraid of one Indian. Dey took dat<lb/>
            Indian an take im ta de plantation, an keep im dar under guard til de<lb/>
            officer come an git im an take im ta de Indian Reservation. An dat was<lb/>
            de las Indian ever seed on de <name type="place">Island of Amelia<location><geo>30.626669 -81.459823</geo></location></name>."<lb/>
         </p>
            </div>
         <pb n="12" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_012.jpg"/>
            <div>
            <head>
               <hi rend="center"><label rend="case(allcaps)">Chapter III<lb/>
                  Slave Days in <name type="place">Florida</name></label><lb/>
               </hi>
            </head>
            
         <p rend="indent">
           By the turn of the ninteenth century the number of Negro slaves<lb/>
            in the state, as compared to those in neighboring states, was still<lb/>
            small. For the most part they were runaways from the <name type="place">United States</name><lb/>
            who had been accepted by the <name type="person_group">Seminole</name>. There were some hundreds in<lb/>
            and around <name type="place">St. Augustine</name>, and a few at <name type="place">St. Marks</name>, <name type="place">Pensacola</name>, and other<lb/>
            smaller communities. In most cases they paid a tribute of farm produce<lb/>
            to the Indians, under a system similar to both medieval surfdom and<lb/>
            modern share-cropping. With none of the stringent bondage of <name type="place">Georgia</name><lb/>
            and the <name type="place">Carolinas</name>, the Negroes had their own towns and live stock, and<lb/>
            led an unsupervised existence.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Though the number of slaves in <name type="place">Florida</name> grew slowly, they increased<lb/>
            by leaps and bounds in <name type="place">Georgia</name>. Originally settled in <date when="1738">1738</date> as a buffer<lb/>
            free state between the slave-holding <name type="place">Carolinas</name> and semi-free <name type="place">Florida</name>,<lb/>
            <name type="place">Georgia</name> lost little time in becoming a slave state when the huge planta<lb break="no"/>
            tions, with their need for hundreds of slaves, pushed steadily towards<lb/>
            the <name type="place">Florida</name> border.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            The transfer of <name type="place">Florida</name> from <name type="nation">Spain</name> to <name type="nation">America</name> early in the nine<lb break="no"/>
            teenth century heralded the approach of slave-holding on a large scale.<lb/>
            Agricultural expansion began; plantations appeared on the <name type="place">Apelachicola</name>,<lb/>
            <name type="place">Suwannee</name>,<lb/> and <name type="place">St. Johns</name>,<lb/> Rivers, and the section around <name type="place">St. Augustine</name>,<lb/>.<lb/>
         </p>
               <pb n="13" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_013.jpg"/>
         <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline">Classification of Slaves</hi>. With few exceptions, the slaves of<lb/>
            <name type="place">Florida</name> fell into one of the two major classifications: farm workers, who<lb/>
            constituted the vast majority, and house slaves, the few lucky men<lb/>
            and women who tended the grounds and homes of their masters. Both men<lb/>
            and women worked in the fields, raising cotton, tobacco, and food crops.<lb/>
            There were a few mechanics, blacksmiths, carpenters, and workers skilled<lb/>
            in other crafts, who were, chiefly confined to the larger plantations.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline">The Larger Plantations</hi>. Among the larger slaveholders was<lb/>
            <name type="person">Zephaniah Kingsley</name> on <name type="place">Fort George Island<location><geo>30.439425 -81.437700</geo></location></name>, near the mouth of the <name type="place">St.<lb/>
               Johns River</name>s. <name type="person">Kingsley</name> was concerned with slaves in a number of ways.<lb/>
            He brought them from <name type="place">Africa</name> in his own ships, worked them on his<lb/>
            plantation, and trained them for sale in the slave markets. This<lb/>
            training was many-sided; suffice it to say that at the sales in the<lb/>
            vicinity there were usually offered a number of slaves who were<lb/>
            described as "<name type="person">Kingsley</name>'s niggers," who brought more per head than the<lb/>
            others, because of their special training as either house or field<lb/>
            hands. <name type="person">Kingsley</name>'s slaves belonged to no unscrupulous pirate dealing<lb/>
            in human flesh. Though he was a professional slavedealer, he had un<lb break="no"/>
            usual standards. At the height of his slave trade he wrote a book,<lb/>
            <hi rend="underline">The Patriarchal System of Society</hi>, concerning the merits of slave<lb break="no"/>
            holding as a means of disseminating certain benefits to heathens.<lb/>
            <name type="person">Kingsley</name> married a Negro woman, stating in his will that he respected<lb/>
            fully the African rites that had united them. He provided liberally<lb/>
            for his mulatto descendants.<lb/>
         </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_014.jpg"/>
         <p rend="indent">
            In the vicinity of <name type="place">Jacksonville</name>, <name type="place">Mandarin</name>, and <name type="place">St. Augustine</name><lb/>
            there were large plantations, and also public markets where slave<lb/>
            sales were held regularly. In <name type="place">West Florida</name>, particularly in <name type="place">Columbia</name>,<lb/>
            <name type="place">Madison</name>, and <name type="place">Jackson</name> counties, plantations were large than those in<lb/>
            <name type="place">East Florida</name>. In <name type="place">Pensacola</name> there were dozens of liberated and semi<lb break="no"/>
            free slaves working on government forts and properties.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            One of the larget plantation in <name type="place">West Florida</name> was <hi rend="underline"><name type="place">El Destino</name></hi>,<lb/>
            settled in <date when="1826">1826</date>. Cotton was the chief product of cultivation, and<lb/>
            corn, oats, sugar cane, potatoes and rice were also grown; in fact,<lb/>
            the aim was to make the plantation self-sufficient. Relations between<lb/>
            master and slaves on this plantation were relatively commandable. Few<lb/>
            changes of ownership occurred, as testified by the appearance of the<lb/>
            same names in the tabulations and reports of the plantation for about<lb/>
            thirty years. Even the War between the States brought only a slight<lb/>
            change among the hands, due to the fact that middle <name type="place">Florida</name> was never<lb/>
            occupied by Federal troops. After the war, many of the ex-slaves<lb/>
            remained to work the old fields on a share-crop basis. In <date when="1919">1919</date> the<lb/>
          <hi rend="underline"><name type="place">El Destino</name></hi> plantation was sold by descendants of the original owner<lb/>
            for $70,000. It is 17 miles east of <name type="place">Tallahasse</name>, and its magnificent<lb/>
            oaks and shrubbery attract frequent visitors. It is now the property<lb/>
            of Whitehouse of <name type="place">New York City</name>.<lb/>
         </p>
               <pb n="15" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_015.jpg"/>
         <p rend="indent">
            The <name type="place"><name type="person">Hanson</name> plantation</name> near <name type="place">St. Augustine</name> raised sugar cane, veg<lb break="no"/>
            etables and fruits. It occupied the exact site of the present <name type="place"><name type="place">Florida</name><lb/>
               Normal and Industrial Institute</name>, one of the outstanding Negro colleges<lb/>
            in the state. What are now <name type="place">Jefferson</name> and <name type="place">Leon</name> counties, and other sec<lb break="no"/>
            tions of the cotton-and-tabacco belt, had their large plantations, and<lb/>
            there were others farther west and south.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline">Slave Diets</hi>. While the food of the slaves seems to have been about<lb/>
            the same on most plantations, the conditions under which it was eaten<lb/>
            varied greatly. Some former slaves state that when the work signal<lb/>
            sounded in the morning they had to "Git it an run," that is, snatch up<lb/>
            a sandwich or chunk of bread they had prepared the night before and eat<lb/>
            it on the way to the field or after arriving there. Others were allowed<lb/>
            adequate time for breakfast.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Lunch on some plantations was eaten in the field in the greatest<lb/>
            possible haste; on others, lunch time meant a rest period of varying<lb/>
            length for the slave who could eat rapidly.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Supper was the slave's important meal. This was always eaten in<lb/>
            his cabin, with whatever family he might be fortunate enough to have.<lb/>
            It was cooked by his wife or mother, after her own duties were finished<lb/>
            in the field or at the Missus' house. The children, tended during the<lb/>
            day by a Negro woman, shared supper with their parents. Supper usually<lb/>
            consisted of some kind of meat--often only salt pork--green vegetables,<lb/>
            potatoes, corn bread, and coffee or some substitute. The most common<lb/>
            substitute for coffee was corn or corn meal, parched until dark brown,<lb/>
            <pb n="16" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_016.jpg"/>
            then boiled. When this was not available, okra seeds and even<lb/>
            parched potatoes were used.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            The corn meal was cooked into either pones or pan bread. Corn<lb/>
            bread was sometimes baked in the top of an iron spider, a large pan<lb/>
            wit a compartment in which coals were heaped. Potatoes were wrapped<lb/>
            in the large leaves of the tannion plant, or sometimes in green corn<lb/>
            shucks, and roasted in live coals. Green corn was an occasional and<lb/>
            welcomed treat.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            While these were the rations that the master provided and knew<lb/>
            about, other items were consumed that did not so readily come to his<lb/>
            attention. Among these was the wild squash, which grew in the woods<lb/>
            of west <name type="place">Florida</name>. Slave owners had little objection to its use by<lb/>
            slaves, except that a trip to the woods was required to procure it,<lb/>
            involving the possibility of escape.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Pilfered eggs were another common dish. Where stumps and under<lb break="no"/>
            brush were burned to clear the land, the ground beneath the fire would<lb/>
            hold an intense heat. Eggs stolen from nests would be surreptitiously<lb/>
            buried near the fire; a few minutes later a loud crack would inform the<lb/>
            slave that his baked egg also ready to eat. Potatoes, when not included<lb/>
            in the regular fare, were also stolen and cooked in this manner. On<lb/>
            large plantations the problem of feeding all of the Negro children was some<lb break="no"/>
            times solved by "toting" milk to a long wooden trough, tossing in corn<lb/>
            bread and other morsels, and letting the children line up with their<lb/>
            spoons.<lb/>
         </p>
               <pb n="17" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_017.jpg"/>
         <p rend="indent">
            Sundays and special occasions would bring dessert as an addition<lb/>
            to the slave's meal. This would sometimes be potato bread made of<lb/>
            sweet potatoes boiled until soft, then mashed, combined with the grease and<lb/>
            coal meal, and baked till brown. None of the <name type="place">Florida</name> ex-slaves reports<lb/>
            the use of sugar in their cabins; when sweetening of any kind was af<lb break="no"/>
            forded, it was sugar-cane molasses.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            The amount of meat eaten depended entirely upon the master; it was<lb/>
            not considered a necessary part of a slave's diet. Some plantations<lb/>
            provided it at least once a day, and kept well-filled storehouses.<lb/>
            Others parceled it out very seldom, and then only the unused parts of<lb/>
            the hogs or cows killed for the master's use. Frequent "disappearance"<lb/>
            of hogs was a consequence.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            One commodity, salt, seems to have given both master and slave<lb/>
            great cause for worry; the master, because of the expense and trouble<lb/>
            often necessary to secure it, and the slave because he so frequently<lb/>
            went without it. In many cases it was obtained from boiled sea-water;<lb/>
            one plantation owner near <name type="place">Monticello</name> took a team and slave and traveled<lb/>
            40 miles to the <name type="place">Gulf of <name type="nation">Mexico</name></name>, and there boiled down a supply. The<lb/>
            process was slow and laborious.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            The slaves had other methods of obtaining it. On some plantations<lb/>
            they would scrape the floor of the smokehouse at every opportunity.<lb/>
            One slave would wash the smokehouse floor, carefully saving the scrub<lb break="no"/>
            water; with this brine she would do her seasoning. Another slave<lb/>
            remembers chopping un a board from the smokehouse floor, and using the<lb/><!-- May need to change word "up?" -->
            wood chips for seasoning. The wood, soaked with the meat-drippings, im<lb break="no"/>
            parted a flavor of both meat and salt.<lb/>
         </p>
               <pb n="18" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_018.jpg"/>
         <p rend="indent">
            Scraps of fat or drops of grease were seldom wasted. Grease<lb/>
            from the "big house" and cabin alike was carefully kept in a special<lb/>
            container.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline">Soap, Candles, and Cowhide</hi>. Oak or cypress wood was burned and<lb/>
            the ashes placed in a vat or tub. The ashes were soaked in water for<lb/>
            several days, and the water then drawn off into a pot. In this pot<lb/>
            was placed the accumulated grease, and the whole mixture boiled for<lb/>
            several hours. The potash and grease mixture was then poured out to<lb/>
            cool, after which it was cut into squares. The plantation then had its<lb/>
            supply of soap.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Beef tallow, melter and poured into moulds, provided light for<lb/>
            the plantation. Some of the slaves were adept at placing strings in<lb/>
            the hardening tallow in such a manner that creditable candles would<lb/>
            result. On many plantations, only the master's house used the candles;<lb/>
            the Negro cabins were illumnated by fireplace.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Oak wood was also used when leather was to be tanned. Oak chips<lb/>
            or ashes would be soaked in water, as in potash making, and when that<lb/>
            solution reached a certain strength cowhides were placed in it. After<lb/>
            a few days the hides were taken out and dried, and later fashioned into<lb/>
            shoes, harnesses, and other articles.<lb/>
         </p>
               <pb n="19" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_019.jpg"/>
         <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline">Clothing</hi>. Both mistress and maid during <name type="place">Florida</name>'s slave period<lb/>
            had a taste for gay color in dress. Cloth was made on many plantations<lb/>
            by the women with the help of those children too young to work in the fields.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            White cotton cloth was dyed in a number of ways. The indigo<lb/>
            plant--once grown in <name type="place">Florida</name> commercially and still found in a wild<lb/>
            state--provided blue coloring, and the pokeberry gave a desirable red.<lb/>
            Oak bark provided varying shades of brown, and the walnut an inerad<lb break="no"/>
            icable dark brown.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            On some plantations the owners gave the Negro women a white cotton<lb/>
            dress once or twice a year, which was dyed to afford a gay change of<lb/>
            dress for "Sunday-go-to-meetin."<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            The daily attire of the slaves was not generally colorful; the<lb/>
            men wore coarse pants and shirt, and the women wore tight bodices and<lb/>
            full gathered skirts. These were the days of half a dozen petticoats.<lb/>
            Occasionally a slave became the proud possessor of her mistress' dis<lb break="no"/>
            carded hoop skirt, but this was unusual. Hoops were expensive, so<lb/>
            grape vines and bamboo often served as hoops for both mistress and<lb/>
            slaves.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline">Amusements</hi>. Plantation life was not always all work and no play.<lb/>
            There were definite occasions for merriment and even celebrations on<lb/>
            many plantations; these ran from the usual visits of individuals or<lb/>
            small groups to occasional festivals. <name type="person">Thomas</name> and <name type="person">Bryant Folsom</name>, in<lb/>
            <pb n="20" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_020.jpg"/>
            <name type="place">Jefferson County</name>, often stages rival parties to see which could give<lb/>
            his slaves the better times. There were others who let their slaves<lb/>
            go to other plantations for affairs at certain times.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Christmas was the lost<!-- May need to change word "most?" --> popular of these occasions. On some<lb/>
            plantations there were parties with extra food and meat allotments<lb/>
            from the master's house, and other presents for the slaves. Few ex<lb break="no"/>
            slaves remember ever having been overlooked when it came to Christmas<lb/>
            presents. The men usually recieved new shoes or srticles of clothing,<lb/>
            while the women were made happy with household articles or discarded<lb/>
            dresses of the mistress. Several plantations gave their slaves cash<lb/>
            presents.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            New Year brought a short day in the field or a holiday, and anoth<lb break="no"/>
            er gift of extra food, with the highly prised meat allotment. New<lb/>
            Year's night, on some plantations, was spent singing, dancing and visiting.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            The harvesting of a crop, such as tabacco, cotton or sugarcane,<lb/>
            was cause for celebration also. In at least a few cases there were<lb/>
            celebrations that corresponded very closely to the Green Corn Dance of<lb/>
            the <name type="person_group">Seminole</name>, though just how much the <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> dance influenced the<lb/>
            slaves is uncertain.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Occasionally, visits to neighboring plantations would be made<lb/>
            on a large scale. These would bring forth carefully hoarded stores<lb/>
            of molasses, meal, potatoes and other foods; if there was music on<lb/>
            improvised banjos and much jollity, the master might even contribute<lb/>
            <pb n="21" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_021.jpg"/>
            a few delicacies for the entertainment of the visitors. Singing and<lb/>
            dancing around a fire in front of one of the cabins would last late<lb/>
            inbto the night and any previously missed opportunities for courting<lb/>
            were eagerly seized by the younger couples. Young husbands and wives,<lb/>
            living apart, made the most of these occasions.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline">Marriage, Religion, and Baptism</hi>. Some plantation owners not <add type="caret">only</add> per<lb break="no"/>
            mitted but enouraged the marriage of their slaves. Then both parties<lb/>
            lived on the same plantation, they might be given both legal and rel<lb break="no"/>
            gious ceremony to seal their union; if one party lived on another<lb/>
            plantation, such a master might even intercede for the purchase of the<lb/>
            other party.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            On other plantations, though, the marriage ceremony took the form<lb/>
            of "jumping over the broom." This was performed after work hours in<lb/>
            some cabin. In the presence of a few slaves a boom was placed on the<lb/>
            bride would leap across the broom, then the groom, and so they were<lb/>
            married.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Religious teaching was often permitted; perhaps the <name type="person_group">Spanish</name> in<lb break="no"/>
            fluence was responsible for this. Even after emancipation of the slaves<lb/>
            there were no churches for Negroes in <name type="place">St. Augustine</name> but Negro Catholic once,<lb/>
            and protestant Negro missionaries were beaten by Negro Catholics when<lb/>
            they attempted to establish Baptist and Methodist churches. Throughout<lb/>
            <name type="place">Florida</name> there was a suspicion that protestant missionaries were aboli<lb break="no"/>
            tionists. Some slaves were forbidden to attend church meetings. At<lb/>
            <pb n="22" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_022.jpg"/>
            the hamlet of <name type="place">Sixteen, Florida</name>, one slave woman saw her son killed for<lb/>
            attending church, and was threaened with death herself if she did not<lb/>
            cease weeping over the incident.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            The white churches which allowed slaves to attend required that<lb/>
            they enter by a separate door, and sit in a section reserved for them.<lb/>
            Some churches held special services designed for slaves after the reg<lb break="no"/>
            ular sermons.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            By <date when="1856">1856</date>, however, only a few owners refused to permit their slaves<lb/>
            to listen to service in either the white churches or colored meetings;<lb/>
            attendance at religious services had come to be considered an indis<lb break="no"/>
            pensable activity of slaves on most <name type="place">Florida</name> plantations. Reasons for<lb/>
            this change appear to have been--from the standpoint of slave-owners--<lb/>
            largely economic. Preachers, whether white or Negro, generally based<lb/>
            their exortations on the theme: "Love your master. Don't steal. Be<lb/>
            obedient." In return, slaves were assured that they would be rewarded<lb/>
            with heavenly bliss after death; if they deviated from the code, they<lb/>
            could expect nothing better than the fires of hell. The inference was<lb/>
            also made that disobedient slaves would experience a more familiar form<lb/>
            of damnation while they lived.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Baptismal services were held at or near the larger plantations.<lb/>
            After several weeks had been spent prepring the slaves for "acceptance<lb/>
            of Christ," a large enough group would be ready to hold a "Christnin."<lb/>
            Robed in a single dress-like garment of white, the candidates, men and<lb/>
            women, would be taken to some nearby stream. There the preacher would<lb/>
            <pb n="23" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_023.jpg"/>
            go through an elaborate ceremony, accompanied by the singing and "fall<lb break="no"/>
            ing out" of the witnesing slaves. "Falling out" the other slave would<lb/>
            continue their singing and shouting. A triumphal march back to the<lb/>
            water. These ceremonies take place today in many rural communities.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Some plantations permitted regular Sunday school classes, some<lb break="no"/>
            times taught by kindly young daughters of the masters or by house<lb/>
            slaves who could read. Other owners made attendance at the Sunday<lb/>
            meetings compulsory. One slave complains that "after we had worked in<lb/>
            de fields fun half-pas four ta half-pas six ever day in de week, we'd<lb/>
            have ta git up at sebm o'clock on Sunday an listen to d preacher."<lb/>
            At least one plantation is known to have used a full-time preacher, who<lb/>
            wasn't too well-liked "cause he went roun dressed up in a high hat all<lb/>
            de time, watchin us an meddlin and tellin de master everthing we done.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline">Beliefs, Superstitions, Cures</hi>. The constant efforts of the<lb/>
            preachers to center the slaves' thoughts on the hereafter did not stop<lb/>
            them from having an elaborate system of sgns, beliefs, and cures for<lb/>
            their multitudinous earthly troubles. Many of their remedies for ill<lb break="no"/>
            ness, like ipecac, were no doubt efficacious, though their potency was<lb/>
            usually given a supernatural rather than a natural explanation.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            A reported aid to escape was the mixture of "graveyard dust an<lb/>
            lightwood splinters that my Uncle Bob an Uncle July smeared on their<lb/>
            <pb n="24" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_024.jpg"/>
            feet when they run away, an <name type="person">Bob Amos</name>' hounds coulden break the spell<lb/>
            an ketch em." While they were hiding in the woods, cotton seed sprin<lb break="no"/>
            kled on the ground kept them from getting cold.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Hogs, according to the belief of the slaves, could see the wind<lb/>
            with ease and it was always blood-red to them. Early on every Christ<lb break="no"/>
            mas morning all animal were believed to talk fluently. The rind of<lb/>
            a watermelon worn around the neck would eliminate all trouble for a<lb/>
            child in teething, and if melons were not in season, a pearl button<lb/>
            would accomplish the same result. A concoction of boiled wasps' nests<lb/>
            and vinegar would aid the child who was slow in learning to walk. Occa<lb break="no"/>
            sional nursing at the breast by a child of two, three, or more years<lb/>
            would save it from trouble with its teeth and bones. Sheep droppings<lb/>
            made an excellent remedy, used either as a liniment or a medicine and<lb/>
            the ipecac plant was a great favorite for any ailment of stomach or<lb/>
            respiratory tract.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline">Slave Education</hi>. Education for slaves was almost entirely voca<lb break="no"/>
            tional that is, they were trained in order to increase their efficiency<lb/>
            and value to their owner. On some plantations reading and writing was<lb/>
            permited, and on at least one, <name type="person">Kingsley</name>'s, it was part of the intelli<lb break="no"/>
            gent slave's training. In <name type="place">Leon County</name> one master's daughter spent each<lb/>
            Sunday teaching the slaves to read and write. On a plantation near<lb/>
            <name type="place">Pensacola</name>, slaves caught attempting to write had their finger cut off.<lb/>
         </p>
               <pb n="25" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_025.jpg"/>
         <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline">Eugenics to Order</hi>. The rapid breeding of slaves, to replace<lb/>
            deaths and for purposes of sale and trade, was desired on most planta<lb break="no"/>
            tions. Thus there were women whose chief function was that of<lb/>
            "breeder," and whose daily chores were confined to light work around<lb/>
            the house. Their job was to have big healthy children, and they were<lb/>
            mated with the most promising of the men. It was not unusual for the<lb/>
            breeder to bear twelve of fourteen children during her active life.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Some of the Negro women were mated with their white master or<lb/>
            overseer; this resulted in the much sought-after mulattoes, used as<lb/>
            house slaves. They were thought to be less strong than other Negroes,<lb/>
            and care was used in working them.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Another plantation job was that of "suckler." Her duty was to<lb/>
            nurse the babies while their mothers were at work in the fields.<lb/>
            Still others tended the young children. Many women did not leave their<lb/>
            work in the fields until their labor pains started, and their babies<lb/>
            were given to sucklers when only a few weeks old.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline">Treatment of <name type="place">Florida</name> Slaves</hi>. Conditions under which <name type="place">Florida</name> slaves<lb/>
            lived varied greatly. From the kindnesses of the <name type="person">Kingsley</name>s, <name type="person">Sanderson</name>s,<lb/>
            and <name type="person">Blount</name>s--all of whom were known to discharge brutal overseers--<lb/>
            treatment went to other extreme as on the <name type="place"><name type="person">Lopez</name> plantation</name> near <name type="place">St.<lb/>
            Augustine</name>, where ex-slaves say they were beaten for hours at a time by<lb/>
            the master himself.<lb/>
         </p>
               <pb n="26" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_026.jpg"/>
         <p rend="indent">
            There seem to have been few really "hard" plantations in<lb/>
            <name type="place">Florida</name>  than in other states where there were more and larger planta<lb break="no"/>
            tions. Some owners, like the <name type="person">Sandersons</name> and <name type="person">Reids</name> in <name type="place">Duval County</name> ,<lb/>
            and the <name type="person">Hansons</name> in <name type="place">St. Johns</name> , carefully avoided separating families<lb/>
            when buying or selling slaves; others almost never sold a slave, and<lb/>
            refused to employ overseers who beat slaves. One slave remembers<lb/>
            that he was never forced to do any strenuous work as long as he beat<lb/>
            the slaves of the other masters at marbles; another was permitted to earn<lb/>
            extra money by distilling moonshine. Several recall having been per<lb break="no"/>
            mitted to plant small gardens for themselves near their cabins.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            That some of these kind masters may have been known to the slaves<lb/>
            is evident in the fact that there are several instances of Negroes who<lb/>
            voluntarily entered slavery in order to secure the freedom of others.<lb/>
            One such instance occurred on the <name type="place"><name type="person">Cone</name> plantation</name> in <name type="place">Columbia County</name> ;<lb/>
            another three years period of voluntary slavery was entered nto in the<lb/>
            vicinity of <name type="place">St. Augustine</name> . In this case the sum of $850 had to be paid<lb/>
            in work. In <name type="place">Columbia County</name> , <name type="person">Cato Smith</name>, a free <name type="place">Connecticut</name>  Negro<lb/>
            traveling in <name type="place">Florida</name>  out of curiosity, entered into a 7-year period<lb/>
            of slavery in order to free the woman he wanted to marry. He was for<lb break="no"/>
            tunate and within four years he had his wife, as well as a small in<lb break="no"/>
            come from his labor.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Slaves reacted differently to cruel masters; some were thoroughly<lb/>
            broken in spirit, while others resorted to retaliation, not always<lb/>
            open, but smetimes quite effective. One woman, tiring of the beat<lb break="no"/>
            ings given her by an overseer, hacked him to death with a hoe; anoth<lb break="no"/>
            <pb n="27" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_027.jpg"/>
            or killed the Negro overseer on her master's plantation when he goaded<lb/>
            her too far, then went to her master and bade him punish her as he saw<lb/>
            fit. She says that he sent her to a cabin by herself and told her to<lb/>
            "keep your mouth shut and only do whatever work your mistess has for<lb/>
            you to do and behave yourself."<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline">Escapes</hi>. Due to the friendliness of the <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> Indians and the<lb/>
            relative inexperience of <name type="place">Florida</name> slave owners in practices of slavery,<lb/>
            the number of Negroes who escaped or attempted escape was still high<lb/>
            as late as <date when="1835">1835</date>-<date when="1840">40</date>; after that time many plantations employed the<lb/>
            "buck-and-gag" treatment for runaway slaves, a punishment wherein the<lb/>
            slave was doubled about a hoe, shovel or board, tied, and left to lie<lb/>
            in the hot sun. The "bell-and-stocks" system, where an iron halter<lb/>
            was placed around the waist and neck of the slave and a loud bell<lb/>
            attached to it, was another popular method of punishment. And of<lb/>
            course recalcitrant slaves could always be sold to other masters.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent"> Some masters dealt summarily with slaves who attempted to escape;<lb/>
            others regarded the desire to seek liberation as natural, and even<lb/>
            forbade the patrollers to punish their escaped slaves before or upon<lb/>
            returning them. One slave escaped three times as a boy, returned vol<lb break="no"/>
            untarily twice, and when his master went to war he remained on the<lb/>
            plantation as the most dutiful servant of his mistress. Another<lb/>
            escaped slave was captured, severely beaten, and buried alive; other<lb/>
            slaves exhumed him, revived him, and sent him on his way again. Nor<lb/>
            was he recaptured.<lb/>
        </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_028.jpg"/>          <p rend="indent">
            The use of bloodhounds is recorded as early as <date when="1837">1837</date>, when several<lb/>
            were imported from <name type="nation">Cuba</name> and loosened in the <name type="place">St. Johns River</name> area to<lb/>
            regain a number of Indians who had escaped into the country occupied<lb/>
                  jointly by the <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> and free Negroes. On that occasion the blood<lb break="no"/>
            hounds did not succeed in locating a single refugee.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Some escapes were dramatic. One slave was pursued by bloodhounds,<lb/>
            and when tracked to his hiding place in a creak, one by one the bodies<lb/>
            of the hounds who entered the water after him came floating to the<lb/>
            surface. He was not captured.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Despite the fact that escapes were blamed on whatever free Negroes<lb/>
            could be found in a section, many escapes were aided or engineered by<lb/>
            white people who were either abolition-minded or desired slaves<lb/>
            for purposes of traffic.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline">Slave Raiders.</hi> Slave raiders were other "fleas on the body" of the<lb/>
            institution of slavery. <name type="person">Florida Clayton</name>, daughter of a white father and<lb/>
            a free Negro mother, relates that a large covered wagon used to appear<lb/>
            periodically in her section near <name type="place">Tallahassee</name>. The slave raiders would<lb/>
            remain for several weeks, rounding up with hounds unfortunate escaped<lb/>
            slaves, and often even kidnapping slaves from plantations. The cap<lb break="no"/>
            tured slaves were bound, imprisoned in the wagon, and eventually car<lb break="no"/>
            ried army. <name type="place">Florida</name> recalls the names of "Mister Nimrod" and "Mister<lb/>
            Sheehee" as leaders of the enterprise. She believes the slaves were<lb/>
            taken to <name type="place">Alabama</name> and sold.<lb/>
         </p>
               <pb n="29" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_029.jpg"/>
         <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline">Petrollers</hi>. The petrollers were not usually slave raiders.<lb/>
            Their duties were the return of slaves to their masters, and they<lb/>
            were particularly active after the War between the States took many<lb/>
            masters away from their plantations.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            The fear in which the petrollers were held was due to the fact<lb/>
            that they administered beatings to captured slaves before returning<lb/>
            them to their owners. This was the most dread factor the escaping<lb/>
            slave had to take into consideration.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Self-appointed patrollers were not uncommon: sometimes they were<lb/>
            thrill-seeking young hoodlums who saw in the patrol idea an opportunity<lb/>
            to catch and beat unfortunate Negro runaways, and at the same time re<lb break="no"/>
            ceive a considerable profit.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            <name type="person">"Parson" Andrews</name>, a Negro nearing his hundredth birthday and full<lb/>
            of reminiscences about early days in <name type="place">Florida</name>, describes the attempt of<lb/>
            the patrollers to round up a group of slaves and return them to their<lb/>
            plantations. The slaves, he says, were on their way back to their<lb/>
            cabins anyway, but had stopped at the home of another slave for a brief<lb/>
            visit. As they started to leave several of the dread patrollers burst<lb/>
            in. One of the slaves reached into a pile of hot ashes, and threw<lb/>
            them into the faces of the patrollers. In the resulting confusion all<lb/>
            the slaves escaped and returned to their cabins.<lb/>
         </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_030.jpg"/>
         <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline">Abolitioists</hi>. In <name type="place">Leon County</name> near the <name type="place"><name type="person">Campbell</name> plantation</name>, there<lb/>
            were several abolitionists who assisted many of the slaves of the vicin<lb break="no"/>
            ity to gain freedom. And in <name type="place">Jefferson</name> and <name type="place">Madison</name> counties, surrounding<lb/>
            the <name type="person">Panell</name> and <name type="person">Lenton</name> plantations, there were poorer slave owners who<lb/>
            assisted in the escape of slaves from the larger plantations, and then<lb/>
            sold the escaped slaves to itinerant slave traders who came through the<lb/>
            section around the first of the year.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            Among the abolitionaist the case of the <name type="person">Hanson</name> brothers in <name type="place">St.<lb/>
               Augustine</name> is interesting. Both brothers came to <name type="place">Florida</name> during the<lb/>
            early days of the <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> War to fight Indians. One of them returned<lb/>
            to his native <name type="place">New England</name>, thoroughly convinced of the iniquity of the<lb/>
            institution of human bondage; the other remained in the state and estab<lb break="no"/>
            lished a large slave plantation about three miles southwest of <name type="place">St. Augu<lb break="no"/>
               stine</name>. Slaves escaped from one <name type="person">Hanson</name> to be aided in reaching <name type="nation">Canada</name><lb/>
            by the other.<lb/>
         </p>
         <p rend="indent">
            (Add writeup on <name type="person">Jonathan Walker</name>, the white abolitionist who was<lb/>
            branded on the hand at <name type="place">Pensacola</name> in <date when="1844">1844</date>.)<lb/>
         </p>
               <pb n="31" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_031.jpg"/>
               <p rend="indent">
                  <hi rend="underline">Outstanding Slaves</hi>. Among slaves, as among free Negroes, there<lb/>
                  were leaders during <hi rend="underline">ante bellum</hi> days. One of these was <name type="person">Robert Meacham</name>,<lb/>
                  who went about the plantation of his master, near <name type="place">Quiney</name>, for long hours<lb/>
                  each night, with a candle and a well-worn book, teaching his fellow<lb/>
                  slaves to read and write.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  One of the most interesting persons ever to settle in <name type="place">Tallahassee</name><lb/>
                  was <name type="person">George Proctor</name>, a Negro who came to <name type="place">Florida</name> from the <name type="place">Bahamas</name> in<lb/>
                  the <date when="1930">1930's</date>. He entered business as a contractor and built many of the<lb/>
                  present old houses in <name type="place">Tallahassee</name>, among which are three known as the<lb/>
                  "Three Sisters," because of their similarity. <name type="person">Proctor</name> and his wife<lb/>
                  <name type="person">Nancy</name> had a family of six children. In <date when="1849">1849</date> he wanted to go to <name type="place">Cal<lb break="no"/>
                  ifornia</name> in search of gold. He did not have enough money to finance<lb/>
                  the trip, so he mortgaged his wife and children. The mortgage was<lb/>
                  never paid, and the family was sold to <name type="person">George Rutgers</name>, a banker.<lb/>
                  <name type="person">Proctor</name> did not succees as he expected; occasionally he wrote to his<lb/>
                  family, and sometimes he sent them a nugget of gold. He dies before<lb/>
                  the outbreak of the War between the States without having seen them<lb/>
                  again.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  <name type="person">William Bryant</name> of <name type="place">Tampa</name> had cleared away many lots and built<lb/>
                  structures on them for his master before there was any talk of eman<lb break="no"/>
                     cipation. Several slaves had been placed at the head of gangs of<lb/>
                  their fellows on the government reservation at <name type="place">Warrington</name>, near <name type="place">Pensa<lb break="no"/>
                  cola</name>, because of their building ability, and there were a number engaged<lb/>
                  in building, repairing, and other skilled occupations in <name type="place">Tallahassee</name>, <name type="place">Jack<lb break="no"/>
                     sonville</name>, and <name type="place">St. Augustine</name> as far back as 25 years before the war.<lb/>
               </p>
               <pb n="32" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_032.jpg"/>
               <p rend="indent">
                  <hi rend="underline">War between the States</hi>. Negroes figured in the fighting in<lb/>
                  <name type="place">Florida</name> as they did in other state; some of them on the side of the<lb/>
                  Union--there were as many as three battalions of Negroes known to be<lb/>
                  in the states at one time--and many performing individual feats on the<lb/>
                  side of their masters.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  In the latter category were many of the slaves at the <name type="place">Reid's<lb/>
                     plantation</name>, near <name type="place">Jacksonville</name>, where the <name type="place">Southeastern Naval Air Basin</name><lb/>
                  is now located. So loyal were they that when freedom was declared<lb/>
                  they voluntarily remained on the plantation and were later given a<lb/>
                  division of land on it.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  One Negro battalion, stationed in <name type="place">Jacksonville</name> at a time when<lb/>
                  <name type="person_group">Federal</name> troops were burning and levelling the city, came in for com<lb break="no"/>
                  mendatory notice. In describing the destruction being wrought in the<lb/>
                  city, an eye-witness wrote, "It gives me pleasure to report that the<lb/>
                  Negro troops took no part in this vandalism...they had nothing<lb/>
                  whatever to do with it...were merely silent spectators at a sad<lb/>
                  spectacle."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  That there must have been large numbers of Negro troops in the<lb/>
                  state is borne out by one historian's statement that "The <name type="person_group">Union</name> forces<lb/>
                  were finally reduced to about 2,500 or 3,000 men, mostly Negroes."<lb/>
                  This was in <date when="1864">1864</date>.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  From <date when="1863">1863</date> until the end of the War between the States, Negro<lb/>
                  soldiers took part in several Union expeditions into east <name type="place">Florida</name>.<lb/>
                  <pb n="33" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_033.jpg"/>
                  In west <name type="place">Florida</name>, they aided white troops in attacking the villages of<lb/>
                  <name type="place">Zucheeanna</name> and <name type="place">Marianna</name>. At <name type="place">Tampa</name> they were used as military police<lb break="no"/>
                  men. <name type="place">Andrews Bay</name>, and <name type="place">Pensacola</name>, destroying farm crops and other sup<lb break="no"/>
                  plies that were intended for the Confederate Army. They fought in<lb/>
                  the skirmishes of <name type="place">Marianna</name> and <name type="place">Natural Bridge</name>, and played a prominent<lb/>
                  part in the Battle of Olustee.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  It seemed to be a settled policy of the Federal Government to<lb/>
                  use black troops in <name type="place">Florida</name>. A dozen different Negro regiments, re<lb break="no"/>
                  cruited in various parts of the Union, saw service here. Some <name type="person_group">Northern<lb/>
                  army officers</name> were enthusiastic over the soldierly qualities of the<lb/>
                  Negro. <name type="person">Colonel Beard</name>, of the <name type="person_group">48th New York Infantry</name>, who commanded<lb/>
                  Negro troops in the state, reported that the colored men fought with<lb/>
                  astonishing bravery and coolness. <name type="person">General Saton</name> said "The blacks<lb/>
                  are better than white soldiers in this part of the country." Another<lb/>
                  white leader of Negroes, <name type="person">Thomas Wentworth Higginson</name>, stated that<lb/>
                  "nobody knows about blacks who has not seen or read, except<lb/>
                  <name type="person_group">French Zouaves</name>." A Northern war correspondent, present at <name type="place">Fort Myers<location><geo>26.639749 -81.872125</geo></location></name><lb/>
                  when it was attacked by <name type="person_group">Confederate cavalry</name>, wrote that "The colored<lb/>
                  soldiers were in the thickest of the fight and could hardly be re<lb break="no"/>
                  strained; they seemed totally unconcerned of danger and the constant<lb/>
                  cry was 'to get at them'."<lb/>
               </p>
               <pb n="34" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_034.jpg"/>
                  <p rend="indent">
                     Other reports indicate that black troops often gave way under<lb/>
                     determined attacks. They were swept off the field at <name type="place">Olustee</name>,<lb/>
                     <name type="place">Jacksonville</name>, <name type="place">Palatka</name>, and <name type="place">Natural Bridge</name>. Their most valuable ser<lb break="no"/>
                     vices to the <name type="person_group">Union Army</name> wore as guides, spices, and shock troops.<lb/>
                     It was said that <name type="person_group">Southerners</name> were moved to greater effort because<lb/>
                     they realized that a slave race was being employed to subdue them.<lb/>
                     "It is my belief," declared <name type="person">General Saxton</name>, "that scarcely an incident<lb/>
                     in the war caused greater panic throughout the whole <name type="place">South Coast</name> then<lb/>
                     this raid of colored troops in <name type="place">Florida</name>. "I am glad<lb/>
                     to see the accounts of your colored forces at <name type="place">Jacksonville, Florida</name>,"<lb/>
                     he wrote privately to <name type="person">General Hunter</name>, "I see the enemy are driving at<lb/>
                     them fiercely, as is to be expected. It is important to the enemy<lb/>
                     that such a force shall not take shape and grown  and thrive in the<lb/>
                     South, and in precisely the same proportion to us shall it do so."<lb/>
                     Thus <name type="person">Lincoln the Emancipator</name> expressed himself toward the use of Negro<lb/>
                     troops. He believed that the Negro should free himself insofar as<lb/>
                     possible.<lb/>
                  </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  <hi rend="underline">Freedom at Last</hi>. At various times during <date when="1865">1865</date> freedom came<lb/>
                  to the slave on <name type="place">Florida</name> plantations. Few of them seem to have ob<lb break="no"/>
                  served their day of emancipation at the same time; some were liberated<lb/>
                  upon the cessation of the war, others after their crops were harvested.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  Nearly every ex-slave has a different experience to tell of his<lb/>
                  long awaited emancipation. To some it came with the crack of shooting<lb/>
                  <pb n="35" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_035.jpg"/>
                  guns, soldiers riding up and reading long and important-sounding<lb/>
                  proclamations that they couldn't understand, even when blue-clad Negro<lb/>
                  soldiers came to the plantations to help them celebrate. To others<lb/>
                  emancipation meant guarded whisperings, then a long wait for darkness<lb/>
                  so that they could slip away from the masters from whom they still<lb/>
                  expected harshness.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  As in other states, many refused to leave their plantations. In<lb/>
                  <name type="place">Duval</name>, <name type="place">St. Johns</name>, <name type="place">Jefferson</name>, and some other countries many of the<lb/>
                  slaves remained on the plantations where their descedants may be<lb/>
                  found today under a sharecropping arrangement; others were given treats<lb/>
                  of land for their own use.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  Many left immediately for the cities. In <name type="place">Jacksonville</name>, where a<lb/>
                  number of <name type="person_group">Northern soldiers</name> were quartered, temporary houses had to<lb/>
                  be provided for hundreds of them. Confusion naturally resulted,<lb/>
                  intensified by the Negro's entrance into politics, religion, and other<lb/>
                  professional fields. Economic helplessness settled on the Negro's<lb/>
                  shoulders for a time.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  <hi rend="underline">Interviews with Ex-Slaves</hi>. Perhaps no form of social life has<lb/>
                  been more violently defended and condemned than slavery. To some,<lb/>
                  especially when viewed through the softening haze of time, the insti<lb break="no"/>
                  tution of slavery seems like paradise on earth; to others it is the<lb/>
                  opposite. What did the slaves themselves think of the system? Field<lb/>
                  workers of the <name type="person_group"><name type="place">Florida</name> Writers'</name> Project interviewed more than a score<lb/>
                  of ex-slaves and asked them to tell what they remembered. The subjects<lb/>
                  of both the following interviews were women, whether because women live<lb/>
                  longer of are better talkers than men it would be hard to say.
               </p>
               <pb n="36" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_036.jpg"/>
               <p rend="indent">
                  <hi rend="underline"><name type="person">Margarett Nickerson</name></hi>. <name type="person">Margarett Nickerson</name> was born to <name type="person">William<lb/>
                     A. Carr</name> on his plantation near <name type="place">Lake Jackson</name>, <name type="place">Leon County</name>, many years<lb/>
                  ago. She now lived in <name type="place">Jacksonville</name> whit her daughter.
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "<name type="person">Mr. Kilge</name> wus de fust overseer I member; I was big enuf to tote<lb/>
                  meat an stuff fum de smokehouse to de kitchen an to tote water in an<lb/>
                  git wood fur granny to cook de dinner an fur de sucklers who nu-sed<lb/>
                  de babies, an I ca'ied dinners back to de hans.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "On dis plantation was a bout a hunnert haid. We done cookin<lb/>
                  in de fiahplace in iron pots, an de meals wus plenty uf peas, greens,<lb/>
                  cornbread, burn co'n fur coffee. Sometie de master bot coffee fur<lb/>
                  us; we got water fum de open well. Jes fore de   big gun fiahed dey<lb/>
                  fotched my pa fum de bay whar he wus makin salt; he done hear dem<lb/>
                  say de Yankees is comin an' he shure wus glad.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "we done had rice and cotton an co'n an taters what got to be<lb/>
                  tended, an cowhides to be tanned an thread to be spinned. They done<lb/>
                  made de thread into ropes for plow lines.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Ole <name type="person">Marse Carr</name> done feed us, but he didn care what an what, jes<lb/>
                  so you made money, an when you made five an six bales o cotton he<lb/>
                  say you ain done nothin'.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "When de big gun fihed on a Sat'day me an <name type="person">Cave</name> and <name type="person">Minnie Howard</name><lb/>
                  wus settin up co'n fur de plowers to come long an put dirt to em;<lb/>
                  <name type="person">Carr</name> he read de free papers to us on Sunday, an de co'n an cotton<lb/>
                  <pb n="37" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_037.jpg"/>
                  dey had to be tended to. <name type="person">Marse Carr</name> he done tole us he gwine gi us<lb/>
                  de net proceeds"--here she chuckles--"what turn out to be de co'n<lb/>
                  an cotton stalks. Den he ask dem what would stay wid him to step off<lb/>
                  on de right, an dem dat wuz leavin to stop off on de lef.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "My pa made soap fum ashes when he clean de new groun; he done<lb/>
                  take a hopped to put de ashes in, made a li'le stool side de house,<lb/>
                  put de ashes in an po'red water on it to drip. Den at night when he<lb/>
                  git off fum work he done put in de grease an make de soap. I done<lb/>
                  make it myself sometime, an I makes it now.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "My step-pa useter make shoes fum cowhides fur de farm han's on<lb/>
                  de plantation an fur ev'y buddy cep ole Marse and his fambly; deys wus<lb/>
                  diffunt, fine.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "My gramma <name type="person">Phoebe Austin</name>--my mother wus name <name type="person">Rachel Jackson</name> an<lb/>
                  my pa wus name <name type="person">Edwin' Jackson</name>; my mother an uncle <name type="person">Robert</name> an <name type="person">Joe</name> wus<lb/>
                  stole fum <name type="place">Virginny</name> an fetched here. I don know no niggers dat listed<lb/>
                  in de War. I don member much about de War, only when dey started<lb/>
                  talking bout drillin men; <name type="person">Joe Sanders</name> wus a Lootenen. <name type="person">Marse Carr</name>'s<lb/>
                  sons, <name type="person">Tom</name> an <name type="person">Willie</name> went to de War.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  :We didn had no doctors, only de grannies; we mostly used hippecat<lb/>
                  (ipecac) fun medicine.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Lak I done tole you, <name type="person">Kilgo</name> wus de fus overseer I ricollee, den<lb/>
                  <name type="person">Sanders</name> wus nex, an <name type="person">Joe Sanders</name> atter him; <name type="person">John C. Reywood</name> came in<lb/>
                  <pb n="38" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_038.jpg"/>
                  atter <name type="person">Sanders</name>, an when de big gun fiahed <name type="person">ole man Brockington</name> wus dere.<lb/>
                  I never saw a nigger sol but dey ca'ied em fum our house an I never<lb/>
                  seen em no mo.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "We had church wid de white preachers an dey tole us to mine our<lb/>
                  masters and missus an we would be saved. Dey don never tole us nothin<lb/>
                  bout <name type="person">Jesus</name>.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "When de big gun fiahed <name type="person">Old Man Carr</name> had six sacks uf Confederaty<lb/>
                  money whut he wus ca'ing wid him to <name type="place">Athens, Georgia</name>, an all de time<lb/>
                  if any uf us gals whar he wus done ax him, Marse, plasse gi us some<lb/>
                  money"--here she raised her voice to a high, pitiful tone--he say I<lb/>
                  aint got a cent, an right den he would have a chis so full it would<lb/>
                  take a whole passle uv slaves to move it. He had plenty co'n, taters,<lb/>
                  pumpkins, hogs, cows, everything, but he didn gi us nothing but strong<lb/>
                  plain close and plenty to eat; we slep in ole common beds an my pa<lb/>
                  made up li'le cribs an put hay in dem fur de chillan.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Now id you wanted to keep in wid <name type="person">Marse Carr</name> don drap you shoes<lb/>
                  in de fiel an leave em or he'd beat you. You mus tote you shoes in<lb/>
                  de fiel. He'd say, you gun-haided debbil, drappin you shoes an<lb/>
                  evything over de field.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Nw jes lissen, I wanna tell you all I kin, but I wants to tell<lb/>
                  it right. Wait now, I don wanna tell no mistaks an I don wanna lie<lb/>
                  on nobody. I ain mad now an I know taint no use to lie. I'se taking<lb/>
                  my time, I done prayed an got all de malice out o my heart an I ain<lb/>
                  <pb n="39" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_039.jpg"/>
                  gwine tell no lie fer un, an I ain gwine tell no lie on um. I ain<lb/>
                  never seed no slaves sole by <name type="person">Marse Carr</name>; he wus allus ellin me he<lb/>
                  wus gwine sell me but he never did, he sole my pa's fust wife, though.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Dere wus Uncle <name type="person">George Bull</name> he could read an write. Chile, de<lb/>
                  white folks didn lak no nigger whut could read an write. <name type="person">Carr</name>'s<lb/>
                  wife, <name type="person">Miss Jane</name>, useter teach us Sunday school but she didn low us<lb/>
                  to tech a book wid us hans. So dey useter je take Uncle <name type="person">George Bull</name><lb/>
                  an beat him fur nuthin; dey would beat him an take him to de lake an<lb/>
                  put hi on a log an shuv him in de lake, but he allus swim out. When<lb/>
                  dey didn do dat dey would beat him tel de blood run outen him an den<lb/>
                  trow him in de ditch in de fiel an kivver him up wid dirt, haid an<lb/>
                  yeres, an don stick a stick up at his haid. I wus a water toter<lb/>
                  an done stood an seen um do him dat a way more'n once, an I dont stood<lb/>
                  an looked at um tel day went way to de udder rows an den I grabbed de<lb/>
                  dirt offen him an he'd bresh de dirt off an say t'ank-you, git his<lb/>
                  hoe an go on back to work. Dey beat him lak dat an he didn do a t'ing<lb/>
                  to git dat sort of treatmen.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Some uv de slaves run away, lots uv em. Some done get caught<lb/>
                  a when dey ketched em dey put bells on em; fust dey would put a<lb/>
                  iron ban aroun dey neck an anudder one aroun dey wais a rivet em<lb/>
                  together down de back; de bell would hang around de ban aroung dey<lb/>
                  neck an it would right when de slave walked an den dey wouldn git away.<lb/>
                  Some uv em wore dese bells three an four month, an when dey time wus<lb/>
                  up dey would take em offn em. <name type="person">Jake Overstreet</name>, <name type="person">George Bull</name>, <name type="person">John Green</name>,<lb/>
                  <pb n="40" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_040.jpg"/>
                  <name type="person">Ruben Colder</name>, <name type="person">Jim Bradley</name> an a host uv other wore dem bells. Dis<lb/>
                  is whut I know, not whut someboddy else say. I done see dis mysel.<lb/>
                  En missus, when de big gun fiahed, de runaway slaves comed out de<lb/>
                  woods fun all d'rections. We wus in
                de fiel when it fiahed, but I<lb/>
                  members dey wus all glad.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Atter de wat, we work but we got pay fur it.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "<name type="person">Ole man Pierce</name> an some others would call some kine uv a perlitical<lb/>
                  meeting, by I couldn never nderstan whut dey wus talkin bout. We<lb/>
                  didn had no kine uv schools an all I know bout dem is I sent my<lb/>
                  chillens in <name type="place">Leon</name> an <name type="place">Gadsden County</name>."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  <hi rend="underline"><name type="person">Mama Duck</name></hi>.   "Who is the oldest settler, white or colored, that<lb/>
                  you know of in <name type="place">Tampa</name>?"   "See <name type="person">Mama Duck</name>," the grinning elevator boy<lb/>
                  told us, "she bout a hunnert year old."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  So down into the scrub we went and found the old woman hustling<lb/>
                  about from washpot to pump. "I'se mighty busy now, cookin breakfas,"<lb/>
                  she said, "but ef you come back in bout an hour I'll tell you what I<lb/>
                  kin bout old times in <name type="place">Tampa</name>."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  Her dust-covered dog met us with elaborate demonstrations of<lb/>
                  welcome on the return visit.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Owan away f'm here, Spot; dat Comman aint gwine feed you nuthin.<lb/>
                  You keep ye dirty paws offen his close."<lb/>
               </p>
               <pb n="41" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_041.jpg"/>
               <p rend="indent">
                  <name type="person">Mama Duck</name> sat down on a rickety box, motioning us to another on<lb/>
                  the shaky old porch. "Take care you don fall thoo dat ol flo," she<lb/>
                  cautioned. "Hit bout ready to go to pieces, but I'se way behin on<lb/>
                  de rent, so I caint ask em to have hit fixed."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "I see you have no glass in the windows--doesn't it get you wet<lb/>
                  when it rains?"<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Not me, cause I gits ovah on de udder side o de room when hit<lb/>
                  rains. Didn't have no do, neither, when I moved in. Young folks<lb/>
                  round here used to use hit foa co't house afo I come."
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "A what?"<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Court house. Kep a-comin atter I done move in, an I had to shoo<lb/>
                  em away. Dat young rascal comin yonda, he one of em. I claiah to<lb/>
                  goodness..." and <name type="person">Mama Duck</name> raised her voice for the trespasser's<lb/>
                  benafit, "I wisht I had me a fence to keep folks outa my yahd."
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Quu-a-ck, quak, quak," the dresed-up young Negro mocked, as<lb/>
                  he passed on, grinning.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Dat don worry me none; I don let nutin worry me--worry makes<lb/>
                  folks gray-haided," the old woman said, as she scratched her thinly-<lb/>
                  covered head. Three braids, about the length and thickness of an<lb/>
                  eyebrow stuck out at odd angles, and there were not more than a dozen<lb/>
                  gray hairs streaking the rusty black.<lb/>
               </p>
               <pb n="42" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_042.jpg"/>
               <p rend="indent">
                  " sho had planty chance to worry effen I wanted to," she mused,<lb/>
                  as she sipped ice water from a fruit jar foul with dirty fingermarks.<lb/>
                  "Relief folks got me on de black list. Dey give rations to young<lb/>
                  folks what's wukkin and don give me narry a mouthful."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "How's that?"<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Well, in de fust place, dey wanted me to go to de po house. I<lb/>
                  wanted to take mah trunk long, an dey wouldn let me. I got some t'ings<lb/>
                  in dere I be'n havin nigh onto a hunnert year. Got my ol blue-back<lb/>
                  <title level="m">Webster</title>, onlies book I evah had, scusin mah <title level="m">Bible</title>. T'inkl I wanna thow<lb/>
                  dat stuff away? No=o suh!" <name type="person">Mama Duck</name> pushed the dog away from a<lb/>
                  cracked pitcher on the floor and refilled her fruit jar. "So dey<lb/>
                  black-list me, cause I won kiss dey feets. I aint kissin nobody's<lb/>
                  feets--wouldn't kiss my own mammy's."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Well, we's all do lots of things for our mothers that we wouldn't<lb/>
                  do for anyone else."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Mebbe you would, but not me. My mammy put me in a hickery basket<lb/>
                  when I was a day an a half ole with nuttin on but my belly ban an a<lb/>
                  di'per. Took me down in de cotton patch an sot de basket on a stump<lb/>
                  in de bilin sun."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "What in the world did she do that for?"<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Cause I was black. All de othah young uns was bright. My<lb/>
                  granmammy done hear me bawlin an go fetch me to my mammy's house.<lb/>
               </p>
               <pb n="43" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_043.jpg"/>
               <p rend="indent">
                  " 'Dat you, Mammy?' she say, sweet as pie, when granmammy poun<lb/>
                  on de do."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  " 'Don you nevah call me Mammy no mo," granmammy say. Any wo<lb break="no"/>
                  man what'd leave a po li'le mite lak dis to perish to death aint<lb/>
                  fitten to be no datter o mine!' "
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "So granmammy tuk me to raise. I aint nevah seen my mammy<lb/>
                  sence, an I nevah want to."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "What did your father think of the way she treated you?"<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Nevah knew who mah daddy was, an I reckon she didn neither.<lb/>
                  I was bawned at <name type="place">Richard, Virginia</name>; mah sister an brothah be'n dead<lb/>
                  too many year to count--I de las o de fam'ly."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Do you remember anything about the War between the States?<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "What dat?<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "The Civil War, when they set the slaves free."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Oh, de fust war, you mean. I reckon I does--had three childen,<lb/>
                  boys, bawned befo de war. Mah fust mastah didn make us wuk none<lb/>
                  when we was chillens. All I done was play. When I was ole enough<lb/>
                  to wuk, dey tuk us to <name type="place">Pelman, Georgia</name>. I nevah wukked in de fiel's,<lb/>
                  not den, dey allus let me nuss de chillens. Den I got married in<lb/>
                  granmammy's kitchen an went to us own log house. By an by mah mastah<lb/>
                  sole me an mah baby to de man what had de plantation nex to ours-<lb/>
                  his name was <name type="person">John Lee</name>. He was good to me, an let me see mah chillens.<lb/>
               </p>
               <pb n="44" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_044.jpg"/>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "How would he punish his pets?"<lb/>
               </p>
             <p rend="indent">
                  "Sometimes he jes bop em 'erost de yere wid a battlin stick.."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "A what?"<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Battlin stick, lak dis. You don know what a battlin stick is?<lb/>
                  Well, dis yere one. Use hit for washin close. You lif em outa de<lb/>
                  wash pot wid de battlin stick, den you lay em on de battlin block, dis<lb/>
                  yere stump. Den you beat de dirt wid de battlin stick."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Great guns, that stick would knock a horse down!"<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Nossuh, wasn't nigh as bad as some o de othahs got. He had pets<lb/>
                  mongst de mans, too, but dey get hit a li'le wusser dan de wimmons.<lb/>
                  Effen dey wan't too mean, he jes strap em 'crost de sharp side of a<lb/>
                  bar'l an give em a few right smaht licks wid a bull whip."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "H'm--they did get off light, didn't they; and what would he do<lb/>
                  to the bad ones?"<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Well, sometimes dey try to run away; den he mak em cross de<lb/>
                  han's lak dis. Den he tie a rope roun dey wrists an thow hit ovah<lb/>
                  a tree limb. Den he pull em up so dey toes jes touch de gorun an<lb/>
                  smack em on de back an rump wid a heavy wooden paddle, fixed ful o<lb/>
                  holes. Know what dem holes was fur? Ev'y hole mak a blister. Den<lb/>
                  he mak em lay down on de groun whilst he bus all dem blisters wid a<lb/>
                  rawhide whip."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "I should think that would kill any man."<lb/>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_045.jpg"/>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Nevah heard o nobody dyin f'm gittin a beatin. Some couldn wuk<lb/>
                  for a day or two. Sometimes dey thow salt brine on dey backs, or<lb/>
                  smear on turpentine to make it git well quicker."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Well, I suppose you're glad that those days are over."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "Not me. I was aheap bettah off as I is now. Allus had<lb/>
                  sumpin to eat an a place to stay. No such t'ing as gittin on a black<lb/>
                  list. Mighty hard on a pusson ol as me not to git no rations an not<lb/>
                  have no reg'lar job."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "How old are you?"<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "I don know, 'zackly. Mebbe-wait a minute, I didn show you my<lb/>
                  pitcher what wus in de paper, did I? I caint read, but somebody say<lb/>
                  dey put how ol I is under mah pitcher in dat paper."<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  <name type="person">Mama Duck</name> rummaged through a cigar box and brought out a page of<lb/>
                  a <name type="place">Pittsburgh</name> newspaper, dated a year ago. It was so badly worn that<lb/>
                  it was almost illegible, but it showed a picture of the old woman and<lb/>
                  below it was given her age, 109.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  In answer to the question regarding the length of her residence<lb/>
                  in <name type="place">Tampa</name> she said that she didn't remember. "Come here when dey was<lb/>
                  only one sto," she mused. "Hit b'long to <name type="person">Ol Man Muggo</name>. Dey raised<lb/>
                  cotton where <name type="place">Plant City</name> is now. I picked some cotton dere, den I<lb/>
                  come to <name type="place">Tampa</name> an atter a while I got a job nussin Mister <name type="person">Perry Wall</name>'s<lb/>
                  chillen. Cullud folks jes mek out de bes dey could. Some of em lived<lb/>
                  in tents tell dey could cut logs an build houses wid sticks an dirt<lb/>
                  chimbleys."<lb/>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_046.jpg"/>
               <p rend="indent">
                  judging only by the appearence of this wiry old woman, it is<lb/>
                  hard to realize that <name type="person">John Quincy Adams</name> was serving as the country's sixth<lb/>
                  president when <name type="person">Kate Bennett</name> left her unwanted black baby in a <name type="place">Virginia</name><lb/>
                  cotton patch. An interesting study, this patient old crone resigned<lb/>
                  to unpleasant circumstnces over which she has no control, curbing<lb/>
                  her temper in the face of petty annoyances, sitting in a dusty alley<lb/>
                  with her cur dog, as she stolidly waits for the last curtain to fall<lb/>
                  on her long drama of life.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  <hi rend="underline">A Slaveholder Speaks</hi>. Mention has previously been made of a<lb/>
                  slaveholder by no means unfavorably disposed towards the Negroes,<lb/>
                  since he married a Negro woman and left her his property. Perhaps<lb/>
                  his opinion of slaverly is as impartial as any we can have, and it has<lb/>
                  the merit of being practical and not theoretical. The following ex<lb break="no"/>
                  cerpt is from the <title level="m">Patriarchal System of Society</title>, by <name type="person">Zephaniah Kingsley</name>,<lb/>
                  a book which ran through four editions.<lb/>
               </p>
               <p rend="indent">
                  "About 25 years ago, I settled a plantation of <name type="place">St. Johns River</name>,<lb/>
                  in <name type="place">Florida</name>, with about 50 new <name type="person_group">African Negroes</name>, many of whom I brought<lb/>
                  from the coast myself. They were mostly fine young men and women, and<lb/>
                  nearly in equal numbers. I never interfered with their connubial<lb/>
                  concerns, nor domestic affairs, but let them regulate these after<lb/>
                  their own manner. I taught them nothing but what was useful, and<lb/>
                  what I thought would add to their physical and moral happiness. I<lb/>
                  encouraged as much as possible dancing, merriment and dress, for which<lb/>
                  Saturday afternoon and night, and Sunday morning were dedicated; and,<lb/>
                  <pb n="47" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_047.jpg"/>
                  after allowance, their time was usually employed in hoeing their<lb/>
                  corn, and getting a supply of fish for the week. Both men and women<lb/>
                  were very industrious. Many of them made 20 bushels of corn to sell,<lb/>
                  and they vied with each other in dress and dancing, and as to whose<lb/>
                  woman was the finest and prettiest. They were perfectly honest and<lb/>
                  obedient, and appeared quite happy, having no fear but that of offend<lb break="no"/>
                  ing me; and I hardly ever had occasion to apply other correction than<lb/>
                  shaming them. If I exceeded this, the punishment was quite light,<lb/>
                  for they hardly ever failed in doing their work well. My object was<lb/>
                  to excite their ambition and attachment by kindness; not to depress<lb/>
                  their spirits by fear and punishment. I never allowed them to visit,<lb/>
                  for fear of bad example, but encouraged the decent neighboring people<lb/>
                  to participate in their weekly festivity, for which they always pro<lb break="no"/>
                  vided an ample entertainment themselves, as they had an abundance of<lb/>
                  hogs, fowls, corn, and all kinds of vegetables and fruit. They had<lb/>
                  nothing to conceal from me, and I had no suspicion of any crime in<lb/>
                  them to guard against. Perfect confidence, friendship, and good<lb/>
                  understanding reigned between us: they increased rapidly. After a<lb/>
                  few years, this pleasant and profitable state of harmony was in<lb break="no"/>
                  terrupted by the revolution of <date when="1812">1812</date>. A war party of <name type="person_group">Seminole</name> Indians<lb/>
                  attacked the plantation in my absence; caught, bound, and carried off,<lb/>
                  or killed 40 of them, whose reluctance in going with the invaders may<lb/>
                  be imagined from following circumstance. The wife of a young<lb/>
                  man they had tied and were driving off, that her husband, who was too<lb/>
                  strong to be handled and who had his young child in his arms, might<lb/>
                  <pb n="48" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_048.jpg"/>
                  follow; but then he absolutely refused, handing over the child to his<lb/>
                  wife, and saying that she knew best how to take care of it, but that<lb/>
                  his master should never say he was a runaway negro; upon which<lb/>
                  the Indian shot him, and he died next day."<lb/>
               </p>    
            </div>
         <div>
            <pb n="49" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_049.jpg"/>
            <head rend="align(center) case(allcaps)">Reconstruction</head>
            <p rend="indent">
               The Reconstruction Period, <date when="1865">1865</date>-<date when="1876">1876</date>, gave the <name type="place">Florida</name> Negro an<lb/>
               opportunity to enter new fields of activity, from which he had been<lb/>
               barred prior to the War between the States. These included education<lb/>
               religion, politics, and, to a small extent, other cultural pursuits.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
            <hi rend="underline">Politics</hi>. It was necessary to give the Negro a new place in<lb/>
               society. Old concepts had to be changed; the Negro was no longer<lb/>
               private property, he was a private citizen. <name type="person">Abraham Lincoln</name> thought,<lb/>
               perhaps correctly, that he could solve the racial, political, and<lb/>
               economic problems of <name type="place">the South</name>, but an assassin took his life just as<lb/>
               he was beginning the enormous task of rehabilitating <name type="place">the South</name>. Under<lb/>
               less capable guidance, the Reconstruction proved to be a travesty.<lb/>
               The black man became a political pawn in a struggle for power among<lb/>
               misguided idealists, demagogues, profiteers, and overrun by unscrupulous<lb/>
               politicians, although a few of the newcomers had a sincere interest in<lb/>
               bettering the Negro's condition.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               Soon after <name type="person">Andrew Johnson</name> became President, he appointed <name type="person">William<lb/>
                  Marvin</name>, a <name type="person_group"><name type="place">Florida</name> Unionist</name>, as the Provisional Governor of the State,<lb/>
               <name type="person">Marvin</name> called a constitutional convention which met on <date when="1865-10-25">October 25,<lb/>
               1865</date>. In six days' time, the convention annulled the secession<lb/>
               ordinance and ratified the Thirteenth Amendment to the <name type="nation">United States</name><lb/>
               Constitution, thereby abolishing slavery in <name type="place">Florida</name>.<lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="50" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_050.jpg"/>
            <p rend="indent">
               The majority of convention delegates agreed with <name type="person">Governor Marvin</name><lb/>
               that the Negro was not ready for the voting privilege.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               In <date when="1865-12">December 1865</date>, <name type="person">David S. Walker</name>, another standpat Unionist,<lb/>
               was elected Governor on a platform which committed him to the <name type="person">Johnson</name><lb/>
               plan of Reconstruction. He also advocated giving civil but not<lb/>
               political rights to the Negro, and he stated in his inaugural address<lb/>
               "We ought to encourage our colored people to virtue and industry, by<lb/>
               all means in our power. We ought to protect them in all their rights<lb/>
               of both person and property as much as we do white."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               Political developments moved swiftly and the state legislature<lb/>
               convened in <date when="1866-01">January 1866</date>. The biggest problem facing the legislature<lb/>
               was how to assimilate the Negro into the new order. The outcome of<lb/>
               the problem was that the freedmen were, in a general way, admitted to<lb/>
               the same legal status as that held by "free persons of color" before<lb/>
               the War. They were given numerous civil rights but no political rights<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               In the effort to provide the ex-slaves a place in a society no<lb/>
               longer based on slave labor, the legislature of <date when="1866">1866</date> provided for the<lb/>
               organization of colored schools with a state superintendent.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               <name type="person">Ex-Governor Marvin</name> was elected to the <name type="nation">United States</name> Senate, but<lb/>
               the <name type="person_group">Senate</name> refused to seat him. It was charged that <name type="person">Marvin</name> was in<lb break="no"/>
               eligible for the office because too many <name type="place">Florida</name> citizens, meaning<lb/>
               the Negroes, had been disfranchised by the state's election laws.<lb/>
               The unseating of <name type="person">Marvin</name> opened a campaign in <name type="person_group">Congress</name> against the<lb/>
               <pb n="51" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_051.jpg"/>
               <name type="person">Johnson</name> plan of Reconstruction and was instrumental in bringing about<lb/>
               the Congressional Reconstruction Act of <date when="1867">1867</date>. Under this act the<lb/>
               <name type="place">Southern States</name>, except <name type="place">Tennessee</name>, were divided into five military<lb/>
               districts, ruled over by military officers. <name type="place">Florida</name> became part of<lb/>
               the <name type="place">third military district</name>, under the administration of <name type="person">General John<lb/>
               Pope</name>. The same year saw the rise of the <name type="person_group">Freedmen's Bureau</name> in <name type="place">Florida</name>,<lb/>
               and the growth of various secret societies which sought membership<lb/>
               among the freedmen.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               Notable among these societies were the <name type="person_group"><name type="person">Lincoln</name> Brotherhood</name>, which<lb/>
               sought to vote the Negro but not elect him to office, and the <name type="person_group">Loyal<lb/>
               League</name>, which was primarily interested in securing actual equality<lb/>
               for the Negro, even to the extent of electing him to high office.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               The work of the <name type="place">Florida</name> Constitutional Convention of 1865 had<lb/>
               been repudiated by <name type="person_group">Congress</name>, so, in accordance with the Congressional<lb/>
               Reconstructional Convention in <date when="1867-11">November 1867</date>. Black men numbering<lb/>
               16,094 and 11,040 whites registered for the election. The Convention<lb/>
               advocates won the election and a session was set for <date when="1868">January 1868</date> in<lb/>
               the state capital at <name type="place">Tallahassee</name>. Eighteen of the 46 delegates to<lb/>
               the Convention were Negroes.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               The most active Negro at the Convention was <name type="person">Colonel William M.<lb/>
               Saunders</name>, who was very unpopular among the white delegates, since he<lb/>
               was known to be an organizer of the <name type="person_group">Loyal League</name>. The ablast Negro,<lb/>
               however, was the <name type="person">Reverend Jonathon C. Gibbs</name>, who had been educated<lb/>
               <pb n="52" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_052.jpg"/>
               at <name type="place">Dartmouth College</name> and <name type="place">Princeston</name> Seminary. Another type of legis<lb break="no"/>
               lator was <name type="person">Joe Oats</name>, a Negro from <name type="place">Leon County</name>. Many of the humorous<lb/>
               stories about Negro legislators in <name type="place">the South</name> during Reconstruction<lb/>
               days stem from <name type="person">Joe Oats</name>. When elected to <name type="person_group">Congress</name> in 1866, he went<lb/>
               as far as <name type="place">Savannah</name>, where he lived in luxury on the donations of his<lb/>
               supporters in <name type="place">Leon County</name>. On his return home, when the money was<lb/>
               all spent, <name type="person">Oats</name>' friends arranged a celebration for him. Shamelessly,<lb/>
               he reported on the session of Congress, which he had never attended.<lb/>
               As a whole, however, the black delegates were honest representatives<lb/>
               of their race. Only four of the freedmen were illiterate, although<lb/>
               15 of them were ex-slaves.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               The <date when="1868">1868</date> convention developed into a fierce struggle between the<lb/>
               conservative white delegates, on the one hand, and the freedmen and<lb/>
               the radical whites, who were allied against them. One commentator of<lb/>
               the day said of the convention "I wish I could write there is peace,<lb/>
               quiet, order, and honest intent work to make a Constitution for the<lb/>
               people of the State... The hall is more like a gladiatorial arena<lb/>
               than a sober Convention of delegates to form a Constitution for a<lb/>
               State."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               After 28 days of constant strife a climax was reached. The<lb/>
               president of the convention, <name type="person">Daniel Richards</name>, deserted the ex-slaves<lb/>
               and the radical whites, and went over to the conservative faction<lb/>
               led by <name type="person">T.W Ceborne</name>, a white political appointee who had come into<lb/>
               the state to serve as head of the <name type="person_group">Freedmen's Bureau</name> for<lb/>
               <pb n="53" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_053.jpg"/>
               <name type="place">Florida</name>. The <name type="person_group">Osbornites</name> framed a constitution for the state which was<lb/>
               adopted by a majority of the delegates at the convention. It was<lb/>
               modeled in part after the constitutions of <name type="place">Vermont</name> and <name type="place">Missouri</name>.<lb/>
               Among other things, it provided that the state legislature, after <date when="1862">1862</date>,<lb/>
               was to enact a law requiring qualifications for voters, and that the<lb/>
               state should have free tax-supported public schools.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               The first elected Reconstruction Governor of <name type="place">Florida</name> was <name type="person">Harrison<lb/>
                  Reed</name>. On a conservative Republican ticket in <date when="1868">1868</date>, he polled more<lb/>
               than 14,000 votes, while his opponent, <name type="person">J. Walker</name>, a radical, received<lb/>
               less than 2,000 votes. <name type="person">Reed</name> was backed for the office by <name type="person">T.W. Osborne</name>,<lb/>
               the man who had also come out victorious in the Constitutional Con<lb break="no"/>
               vention.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               One political observer said of these two: "<name type="person">Reed</name> and <name type="person">Osborne</name><lb/>
               directed the whole Reconstruction of <name type="place">Florida</name>. <name type="person">Reed</name> was older, grave,<lb/>
               foxy, something of a political shrew... <name type="person">Osborne</name> was young but<lb/>
               penetrative, discreet, gifted with remarkable engineering talent."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               Under pressure from the Negro voters, <name type="person">Governor Reed</name> appointed<lb/>
               one of their race to a place in his cabinet-<name type="person">Jonathon C. Gibbs</name> as<lb/>
               Secretary of State. The latter contended that he, as <name type="nation">United<lb/>
               States</name> Senator from <name type="place">Florida</name>, should make all appointments to office<lb/>
               in the state. <name type="person">Reed</name> insisted that such appointive powers belonged to<lb/>
               the Governor. Their politicl battle grew bitter, and <name type="person">Osborne</name> directed<lb/>
               <pb n="54" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_054.jpg"/>
               his allies in the state legislature to impeach <name type="person">Governor Reed</name>. In<lb/>
               retaliation, <name type="person">Reed</name> sought the aid of Negro legislators, but he was<lb/>
               forced to appoint Gibbs to office before he could hope for their sup<lb break="no"/>
               port. Regardless of the Governor's action in appointing <name type="person">Gibbs</name>, most<lb/>
               of the Negro legislators took an active part in the impeachment pro<lb break="no"/>
               ceedings against him.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               Finally, the impeachment was appealed to the <name type="person_group">state Supreme Court</name>,<lb/>
               and this body ruled that the impeachment was invalid since a quorum<lb/>
               was not present in the senate when the impeachment was carried out.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               One historian points out that the Negro members of the legislature<lb/>
               were inactive most of the time, and took little part in the preceedings,<lb/>
               except in the case of <name type="person">Reed</name>'s impeachment and in their attempts to se<lb break="no"/>
               cure legislation for adequate schools. The same historian states<lb/>
               that the Negro had little part in the many porkbarrel schemes for<lb/>
               plundering the state treasury and swelling the state debt.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               The second session of the legislature convened in <date when="1869-01">January 1869</date>,<lb/>
               and, again, an attempt was made to impeach <name type="person">Governor Reed</name>. This time,<lb/>
               he appealed to the Negroes and they supported him. The impeachment<lb/>
               was quashed by a vote of 45 to 5, indicating the power of the Negro<lb/>
               legislators.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               It was during this period that the Reconstruction reached its<lb/>
               saddest phase. There was considerable lawlessness, although it is<lb/>
               said that <name type="place">Florida</name> experienced less violence than any other Southern<lb/>
               State.<lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="55" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_055.jpg"/>
            <p rend="indent">
               Many of the Negro legislators began to wonder how their white<lb/>
               leaders managed to grow wealthy to grow wealthy on small Government salaries, and<lb/>
               they organized a "smelling committee" to investigate corrupt polit<lb break="no"/>
               ical schemes.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               This was also the period when the <name type="person_group">Ku Klux Klan</name> was most active,<lb/>
               principally in the rural counties of the state, such as <name type="place">Jackson</name>,<lb/>
               <name type="place">Alachua</name>, <name type="place">Escambia</name>, and <name type="place">Leon</name> there was less bad blood between the<lb/>
               white and black races and, consequently, fewer deeds of violence.<lb/>
               Disputes over farm land constituted a leading underlying cause of<lb/>
               racial difficulties during the Reconstruction. Thus antagonisms<lb/>
               flared more often in agricultural districts.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               <name type="person">Gibbs</name>, the Negro Secretary of State in <name type="place">Florida</name>, said of the<lb/>
               period from <date when="1868">1868</date> to <date when="1870">1870</date>, "I really believe the colored people are<lb/>
               better off than they are in other Southern states. I believe there<lb/>
               is more liberty and personal freedom for them here. The poor class<lb/>
               of whites are in a more hopeless condition than the blacks and<lb/>
               particularly in sparsely settled counties."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               An important turn of the <date when="1870">1870</date> election campaign was that the<lb/>
               <name type="person_group">Demacratic Party</name>, composed of the native-white element, began to<lb/>
               reassert itself and cut down the strength of the <name type="person_group">Republicans</name>.<lb/>
               <name type="person">William D. Bloxham</name> of <name type="place">Leon County</name>, who later became Governor, led<lb/>
               the reorganization drive of the <name type="person_group">Democrats</name>. One of the main reasons<lb/>
               for <name type="person">Bloxham</name>'s success in this job was that the <name type="person_group">Afro-Americans</name> were<lb/>
               <pb n="56" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_056.jpg"/>
               becoming thoroughly disillusioned. They saw that when the Negro<lb/>
               sought political power for himself, the white politician forgot his<lb/>
               former friendship for the black man.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               <name type="person">Josiah F. Walls</name>, a freedman from <name type="place">Alachua County</name> was elected<lb/>
               to the <name type="person_group">41st Congress</name>, but was removed after 19 months as the result<lb/>
               of a dubious political maneuver. In spite of this, <name type="person">Walls</name> was nomi<lb break="no"/>
               nated for <name type="person_group">Congress</name> again on the <name type="person_group">Republican</name> ticket in <date when="1873">1872</date>, and he<lb/>
               served throughout the 42nd Congress.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               <name type="person">Casian B. Hart</name>, the white <name type="person_group">Republican</name> Governor elected to office<lb/>
               at the same time as <name type="person">Walls</name>, encountered trouble with his Negro sup<lb break="no"/>
               porters. When the Governor refused to appoint a black man to his<lb/>
               cabinet, the colored legislators threatened to combine their forces<lb/>
               with the <name type="person_group">Democrats</name> and leave him without support To retain his<lb/>
               power, which could only be done by mollifying the Negro politicians,<lb/>
               <name type="person">Hart</name> gave in and appointed <name type="person">Jonathan Gibbs</name> as the first state super<lb break="no"/>
               intendent of education. Although many controversies raged around<lb/>
               <name type="person">Gibbs</name>' administration of the growing <name type="place">Florida</name> school system, it is<lb/>
               generally conceded that he was the ablest and most sincere Negro<lb/>
               in the state during Reconstruction days.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               During the political battles of the <date when="1870">1870</date>'s a new Negro leader<lb/>
               came into prominence. This was <name type="person">John Wallace</name>, a State Senator<lb/>
               representing <name type="place">Leon County</name>, who was later to become historian of the<lb/>
               <name type="place">Florida</name> Reconstruction. He had received a good education at the expense of <name type="person">William D. Bloxham</name> in order that he might teach the<lb/>
               <pb n="57" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_057.jpg"/>
               freedmen on <name type="place"><name type="person">Bloxham</name>'s plantation</name>. Some historians consider him the<lb/> 
               second Negro of the Reconstruction in points of ability and in<lb break="no"/>
               fluence, close behind <name type="person">Jonathan Gibbs</name>. At any rate, he gained a<lb/>
               reputation for political ability and consistently refused to accept<lb/>
               the bribes of renegade <name type="person_group">Republicans</name>.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               After the notorious election of <date when="1876">1876</date>, both the <name type="person_group">Democratic</name><lb/>
               and <name type="person_group">Republican</name> Parties filed charges of fraud at the polls; polit<lb break="no"/>
               ical dissension engulfed the Negro voter and the Negro legislator.<lb/>
               The divided allegiance of the Negro was one cause of his political<lb/>
               downfall; together with the insincerity of many white <name type="person_group">Republican</name><lb/>
               leaders, who never really wished to place the black man in power.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               A third contributing cause of the Negros defeat was that the<lb/>
               <name type="person_group">Freedmen's Bureau</name>, which formerly gave financial assistance to the<lb/>
               Negro, had vanished, along with military rule. He was again de<lb break="no"/>
               pendent upon his master of <hi rend="underline">ante-bellum</hi> days.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               An investigation of the election of <date when="1876">1876</date> produced so much<lb/>
               evidence of fraud that an investigating committee remained in ses<lb break="no"/>
               sion at <name type="place">Tallahassee</name> for an entire month, from <date when="1876-12-13">December 13, 1876</date>,<lb/>
               until <date when="1877-01-13">January 13, 1877</date>.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               After the <name type="person_group">Democratic Party</name> had once more gained political power<lb/>
               in <date when="1876">1876</date>, it kept the control of government in its own hands. The<lb/>
               Negro and his <name type="person_group">Republican</name> alliances gradually passed from the <name type="place">Florida</name><lb/>
               political scene.<lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="58" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_058.jpg"/>
            <p rend="indent">
               <hi rend="underline">Religion</hi>. The advance of the <name type="place">Florida</name> Negro in organizing his<lb/>
               religious worship, once freedom had removed barriers, was more<lb/>
               phenomenal than his successes in other fields. At the close of the<lb/>
               war, several congregations were already established in many parts<lb/>
               of <name type="place">Florida</name>. The ex-slaves had either been worshipping with their<lb/>
               white masters, as with the <name type="person_group">Negro Catholics</name> of <name type="place">Pensacola</name> and <name type="place">St.<lb/>
               Augustine</name>, or were immediately ready to set up churches of their<lb/>
               own, as with the <name type="place">Jacksonville church</name> which is known today as the<lb/>
               <name type="place">Bethel Baptist Institutional Church</name>. Other early Negro religious<lb/>
               groups were the <name type="place">Methodist Episcopal Church</name> in <name type="place">St. Augustine</name>, founded<lb/>
               in <date when="1864">1864</date> and the <name type="place">African Methodist Church</name> in <name type="place">Jacksonville</name>, called<lb/>
               <name type="place">Mount Zion</name>.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               After emancipation, the rural Negro took full advantage of his<lb/>
               privilege to worship God. Lengthy camp meetings, held under the<lb/>
               shade of trees, were popular in all parts of <name type="place">Florida</name>. People from<lb/>
               miles around gathered at the meeting place early in the day and<lb/>
               all-day services were held, the worshippers stopping only long<lb/>
               enough to have dinner. Baskets of food, which every family took<lb/>
               pride in filling to overflowing and fetching to the camp meeting,<lb/>
               were spread upon white cloths upon the ground. As economic cir<lb break="no"/>
               cumstances improved, the congregations were able to build churches,<lb/>
               and the old camp meetings gradually passed from the <name type="place">Florida</name> scene.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               Educti<hi rend="underline">on.</hi> <name type="person">Jonathon Gibbs</name> was as distinguished in the edu<lb break="no"/>
               ational field as in the political field. After serving four years<lb/>
               as secretary of state under <name type="person">Governor Reed</name>, he became <name type="place">Florida</name>'s<lb/>
               <pb n="59" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_059.jpg"/>
               first state superintendent of education in <date when="1872">1872</date>. The state achieved<lb/>
               its first practical system of supervised public education under his<lb/>
               direction. He was instrumental in securing legislation by which a<lb/>
               state board of education was created and funds were appropriated to<lb/>
               maintain schools. The law also required the several counties to<lb/>
               supplement state expenditures.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               The state schools were proceded by a system of free schools<lb/>
               established by the <name type="person_group">Freedmen's Bureau</name> in several cities. A notable<lb/>
               example of the bureau's work was the <name type="place">Jacksonville Negro school</name>,<lb/>
               which was constructed with the financial aid of local white citizens.<lb/>
               This institution grew and expanded, and evolved into the present-day<lb/>
               <name type="place">Staton High School<location><geo>30.352171 -81.672350</geo></location></name>. <name type="place">Cookman Institute<location><geo>29.212173 -81.032388</geo></location></name>, also in <name type="place">Jacksonville</name>, was<lb/>
               founded in <date when="1872">1872</date>. This was another of the bureau's ventures, and<lb/>
               out of it has developed <name type="place">Bethuns-Cookman College<location><geo>29.212173 -81.032388</geo></location></name>, located at <name type="place">Daytona<lb/>
               Beach</name>. Third among the Negro school of higher learning established<lb/>
               after emancipation was <name type="place">Edward Waters College<location><geo>30.343684 -81.683699</geo></location></name>, a <name type="person_group">Methodist</name> institu<lb break="no"/>
               tion founded in <date when="1873">1873</date>. Like the others, it is still in existence,<lb/>
               though it has moved from <name type="place">Live Oak</name>, its first location, to <name type="place">Jacksonville</name>,<lb/>
               where it has a student body of several hundred.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               The ex-slaves, both children and adults, were avid for the<lb/>
               educational opportunities which had previously been denied them.<lb/>
               Makeshift primary schools came into existence in all parts of <name type="place">Florida</name>.<lb/>
               Later, they were gradually absorbed into the state school system.<lb/>
               It was a disturbing question whether of not white and black chil<lb break="no"/>
               dren should attend the same schools. This was finally solved by<lb/>
               <pb n="60" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_060.jpg"/>
               the state constitution of <date when="1885">1885</date>, which provided "White and colored<lb/>
               children shall not be taught in the same school but impartial<lb/>
               provision shall be made for both." Thereafter, segregation was<lb/>
               adhered to, but the educational facilities provided for colored<lb/>
               children were never equal to those provided for the white children.<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
            <pb n="61" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_061.jpg"/>
         <div>
            <note place="marginTop">Suspense- Negro Book</note>
            <head rend="align(center) case(allcaps)">The Years Between</head><lb/>
            <p rend="indent">
               In the more than six decades following the collapse of Recon<lb break="no"/>
               struction, <date when="1876">1876</date>-<date when="1940">1940</date>, the Negro-American people of <name type="place">Florida</name> advanced<lb/>
               in may ways. Their state-wide political power had gradually van<lb break="no"/>
               ished, but a number of Negro Republicans gained prominence by answer<lb break="no"/>
               ing for the Negro vote. Others found careers in the arts, the business<lb/>
               world, and the religious field. Some entered the profession of worked<lb/>
               in the skilled and semi-skilled crafts and trades, and many became<lb/>
               owners of homes, farms, and small businesses. By giving him an impor<lb break="no"/>
               tant place in the state's economic life, these individual achievements<lb/>
               partly compensated for the Negro's losses in the political and social<lb/>
               spheres. Most of the Negro population, however, continued their work<lb/>
               in occupations which required unskilled labor.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               Notable among Negro citizens who distinguished themselves after<lb/>
               the close of Reconstruction are the following:<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               <hi rend="underline"><name type="person">Joseph Edward Lee</name></hi>. He was born in <name type="place">Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</name>, in<lb/>
               <date when="1848">1848</date>, attended public school there, and graduated from <name type="place">Howard Univer<lb break="no"/>
                  sity Law School</name> in <date when="1872">1872</date>. Coming to <name type="place">Jacksonville</name>, he was admitted to<lb/>
               the <name type="place">Florida</name> bar in <date when="1873">1873</date>. Lee served as judge of the municipal court<lb/>
               of <name type="place">Jacksonville</name> from <date when="1880">1880</date> to <date when="1882">1882</date> and was a member of the <name type="place">Florida</name><lb/>
               legislature in <date when="1882">1882</date> and <date when="1884">1884</date>. Appointed collector of customs for<lb/>
               <name type="place">Florida</name> by <name type="person">President Harrison</name> in <date when="1884">1884</date>, he held this position until<lb/>
               <date when="1898">1898</date>. <name type="person">President William McKinley</name> appointed him collector of internal<lb/>
               revenue for <name type="place">Florida</name> in <date when="1898">1898</date>; he served in that capacity under succeeding<lb/>
               <pb n="62" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_062.jpg"/>
               administrations until the advent of <name type="person">President Woodrow Wilson</name> in <date when="1914">1914</date>.<lb/>
               He then resumed his private practice of law. At one time he was<lb/>
               elected clerk of the circuit court at <name type="place">Jacksonville</name> but never served<lb/>
               because the county commissioners failed to approve anu bond he offered.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               <name type="person">Lee</name> was known as a brilliant orator and an astute politician.<lb/>
               He was a delegate to every National Republican Convention from 1880<lb/>
               until his death which occurred in <name type="place">Jacksonville</name>, <date when="1920-04">April 1920</date>.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               <hi rend="underline"><name type="person">Sylvamus H. Hart</name></hi>. Born on a plantation, <name type="place">Darlington County, South<lb/>
                  Carolina</name>, in <date when="1860">1860</date>, of slave parents, <name type="person">Hart</name> came to <name type="place">Jacksonville</name> from<lb/>
               <name type="place">Charleston</name> in <date when="1865">1865</date> with his mother and step-father. The latter taught<lb/>
               him plastering and bricklaying, and he later became a contractor.<lb/>
               After two years as town clerk of <name type="place">LaVilla<location><geo>30.334787 -81.667064</geo></location></name> and one year as tax assessor<lb/>
               of the same place, he established, in <date when="1902">1902</date>, <name type="place">Hart's Bank</name>, the first<lb/>
               bank to be operated by Negroes in <name type="place">Jacksonville</name>. It functioned until<lb/>
               <date when="1913">1913</date> when he closed it voluntarily and paid off his depositors in full.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               <hi rend="underline"><name type="person">Judson Douglass Wetmore</name></hi>. Born in <name type="place">Jacksonville</name> <date when="1870-09-24">September 24, 1870</date>,<lb/>
               he was the son of <name type="person">George W.</name> and <name type="person">Fannie Wetmore</name>.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               His early education was received at <name type="place">Cookman Institute<location><geo>29.212210 -81.032227</geo></location></name>, <name type="place">Jackson<lb break="no"/>
                  ville</name>; he graduated from the law school of the <name type="place">University of Michigan<location><geo>42.278075 -83.738364</geo></location></name>;<lb/>
               and he practiced law in <name type="place">Jacksonville</name> and served with distinction as<lb/>
               a city councilman. <name type="person">Wetmore</name> was noted for his fight against social<lb/>
               segregation, familiarly known as the "Jim Crow" law. He later moved<lb/>
               to <name type="place">New York City</name> where he built up a lucrative practice.<lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="63" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_063.jpg"/>
            <p rend="indent">
               <hi rend="underline"><name type="person">Mathew McFarlin Lewey</name></hi>. Born in <name type="place">Baltimore, Maryland</name>, <date when="1845">1845</date>, <name type="person">Lewey</name><lb/>
               was educated in <name type="place">Baltimore</name> and <name type="place">New York City</name> private schools. He vol<lb break="no"/>
               unteered for service in the Federal Army in fall of <date when="1863">1863</date>, and saw<lb/>
               service at the siege of <name type="place">Fort Wagner</name>, the battle of <name type="place">James Island</name>, and<lb/>
               the slaughter at <name type="place">Honey Hill, South Carolina</name>. He was wounded three<lb/>
               times in the latter engagement while bearing the colors of his regi<lb break="no"/>
               ment.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               After the war he completed a law course and came to <name type="place">Florida</name> in<lb/>
               <date when="1873">1873</date>. For several years <name type="person">Lewey</name> taught school and held a number of<lb/>
               minor political posts. Elected to the state legislature in <date when="1882">1882</date>, he<lb/>
               served for two years, and was a member of the legislative committee<lb/>
               which recommended establishment of the <name type="place">Florida Agricultural and<lb/>
                  Mechanical College<location><geo>30.425796 -84.282857</geo></location></name> at <name type="place">Tallahassee</name>.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               In <date when="1887">1887</date>, at <name type="place">Gainsvile</name>, he founded the  <hi rend="underline">Florida Sentinel</hi>, a<lb/>
               weekly journal. Later it was published at <name type="place">Pensacola</name>, and from <date when="1913">1913</date><lb/>
               to <date when="1934">1934</date> the editorial offices were located in <name type="place">Jacksonville</name>. This<lb/>
               pioneer Negro publisher died <date when="1935-08-18">August 18, 1935</date>.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               <hi rend="underline"><name type="person">Captain James W. Floyd</name></hi>. A Negro mariner, <name type="person">Floyd</name> was born in <name type="place">Duval<lb/>
                  county</name>, <date when="1861-05-04">May 4, 1861</date>. Learning navigation from his father, a tugboat<lb/>
               operator, he later became master of the famous tug <hi rend="underline">Dauntless</hi> which<lb/>
               was engaged in smuggling contraband cargoes from the <name type="nation">United States</name><lb/>
               into <name type="nation">Cuba</name> during the Spanish-American War. <name type="person">Floyd</name>'s skillful naviga<lb break="no"/>
               tion and courage enabled him to pass through heavy patrols on several<lb/>
               occasions.<lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="64" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_064.jpg"/>
            <p rend="indent">
               After the conclusion of the war he was signally honored by the<lb/>
               <name type="person_group">Cuban Government</name>. He was made an honorary member of the <name type="person_group">National<lb/>
               Association of Cuban Revolutionary Veterans</name>, and awarded the Order of<lb/>
               Naval Merit, third class by a recent <name type="person">Cuban President</name>.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               <hi rend="underline"><name type="person">Timothy Thomas Fortune</name></hi>. A native of <name type="place">Matianna</name>, born of slave<lb/>
               parents, <date when="1856-10-03">October 3, 1856</date>, he attended <name type="place">Stanton public school</name> in <name type="place">Jack<lb break="no"/>
               sonville</name>. <name type="person">Fortune</name> gained journalistic experience in the composing<lb/>
               room of the <hi rend="underline">Courier</hi>, a daily <name type="place">Jacksonville</name> newspaper. In <date when="1879">1879</date> he moved<lb/>
               to <name type="place">New York</name>, where he edited first the <hi rend="underline">Rumor</hi>, a Negro publication<lb/>
               of the time, and acquired considerable political influence through<lb/>
               his militant advocacy of Negro rights. <name type="person">Fortune</name> wrote two books which<lb/>
               were widely read, <hi rend="underline">Black and White</hi> and <hi rend="underline">The Negro in Politics</hi>. His<lb/>
               writing career extended from <date when="1880">1880</date> until the <date when="1930">1930</date>'s.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               <hi rend="underline"><name type="person">John R. Scott</name></hi>. A native of <name type="place">South Carolina</name>, <name type="person">Scott</name> was born free,<lb/>
               eight years before the emancipation of the slaves. He moved to <name type="place">Jack<lb break="no"/>
                  sonville</name> in his youth and attended school there. Entered the <name type="person_group">Methodist<lb/>
               Episcopal ministry</name>, and served for several successful years. Later,<lb/>
               <name type="person">Scott</name> entered politics and become deputy collector of internal revenue<lb/>
               for <name type="place">Florida</name>. At one time he was chairman of the <name type="person_group">State Republican<lb/>
               Convention</name>.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               (Add more biographies, and other information to this post-<lb/>
               Reconstruction period.)<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
            <pb n="65" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_065.jpg"/>
         <div>
            <head rend="align(center) case(allcaps)">Contemporary Life</head>
            <p rend="indent">
               <hi rend="underline">Business and the Professions</hi>. <name type="place">Florida</name>'s half-million Negroes<lb/>
               present many evidences in <date when="1940">1940</date> of the progress made by their race<lb/>
               in 250 years, on the peninsula. They have businesses ranging from<lb/>
               the small bootblack stands and restaurants found in every city to<lb/>
               two large insurance companies, one having assets of more than a<lb/>
               million dollars. Each city has from one to several undertaking es<lb break="no"/>
               tablishments, real estate offices, doctors, lawyers, and other pro<lb break="no"/>
               fessional men, in addition to a variety of small enterprises.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               Some cities, like <name type="place">Miami</name>, <name type="place">Tampa</name>, and <name type="place">Jacksonville</name>, have entire<lb/>
               city blocks where Negro stores and offices are the only ones to be<lb/>
               found. There are several sizable hotels operated by and for Negroes,<lb/>
               as well as hospitals and theaters. The <name type="place">Florida</name> Negro has five weekly<lb/>
               newspapers: the <name type="place">Miami</name> <hi rend="underline">Times</hi>, the <name type="place">St. Petersburg</name> <hi rend="underline">Public Informer.</hi> and the <name type="place">St. Augus<lb break="no"/>
                  tine</name> <hi rend="underline">Post</hi>. Among Negro magazines, the <hi rend="underline">Quarterly</hi> of the <name type="place">Florida</name> Agri<lb break="no"/>
               lish from a few columns to two pages of Negro news in what is known<lb/>
               as "star" editions of the papers. Thousands of <name type="person_group">Cuban-Negroes</name> living<lb/>
               in <name type="place">Ybor City</name> read the Spanish-language newspapers published there.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               In the recreational field, there are several Negro beaches and<lb/>
               pleasure resorts, although the race is excluded from nearly all of<lb/>
               <pb n="66" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_066.jpg"/>
               the famed resort areas of <name type="place">south Florida</name>, even to the extent of an un<lb break="no"/>
               written law against the use of separate beaches. <name type="place">Bolita</name>, an almost<lb/>
               universally-played, illegal game of chance which drains millions of<lb/>
               dollars annually from the slim pocketbooks of the Negro laboring pop<lb break="no"/>
               ulation, is partly controlled and operated by negro gamblers and their<lb/>
               henchmen.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               <hi rend="underline">Education</hi>. During the <date when="1937">1937</date>-<date when="1938">38</date> school term, 102,438 Negro children<lb/>
               and youths attended 1,029 public school in the state. At the same<lb/>
               time, there were 281,497 white students in 1,517 schools. It would<lb/>
               appear that, by comparison, the white schools were overcrowded, but<lb/>
               the white schools contained 12,429 rooms and the Negro schools,<lb/>
               1,672 rooms. The reverse condition was true; Negro schools were bad<lb break="no"/>
               ly overcrowded. A need for modernizing Negro school properties and<lb/>
               increasing their facilities was indicated by the fact that 945 were<lb/>
               frame structures and but 84 were brick or concrete. A large per<lb break="no"/>
               centage were rickety, often unsafe, buildings lacking sanitary con<lb break="no"/>
               venienced and a water supply. White students had 767 frame schools<lb/>
               and 750 of brick or concrete, the greater number of which were of<lb/>
               modern construction. The disparity is best explained by the lack of<lb/>
               county support of Negro schools. Nearly all white school have been<lb/>
               constructed by the county governments, but less than two-thirds of<lb/>
               the Negro buildings are county-owned. As an example, <name type="place">Duval County</name>,<lb/>
               with a Negro population of 60,636 in <date when="1935">1935</date>, largest in the state, had<lb/>
               only one Negro high school. Negro public properties in <name type="place">Florida</name><lb/>
               <pb n="67" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_067.jpg"/>
               were valued at $5,148,000 in <date when="1938">1938</date>; white properties at $73,167,000<lb/>
               for the same year.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               Although the state constitution provides that "impartial provision"<lb/>
               shall be made for the  school children of both races, there is a wide<lb/>
               difference in the amounts of money expended for white and Negro edu<lb break="no"/>
               cation. For the <date when="1936">1936</date>-<date when="1937">37</date> term, $17,357,000 were spent for the support<lb/>
               and maintenance of white schools and $2,333,000 for the Negro.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               In <date when="1937">1937</date>-<date when="1938">38</date>, the instructional personnel of Negro schools con<lb break="no"/>
               sisted of 17 supervisors, 47 principals, and 3,063 teachers. The<lb/>
               supervisors, partly supported by the <name type="person">Jeanes</name> Fund, a private philan<lb break="no"/>
               throphy for Negro education, served as liaison agents between county<lb/>
               superintendents of public instruction and Negro schools.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               A <date when="1939">1939</date> survey of the economic status of Negro teachers, issued by<lb/>
               the <name type="place">University of Florida<location><geo>29.644295 -82.354447</geo></location></name>, states the following:<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               "The average salary received by these teachers in <date when="1934">1934</date>-<date when="1935">35</date> was $457.<lb/>
               The lowest salary received was $120 and the highest $1,575. The<lb/>
               <hi rend="underline"><name type="place">Florida</name> School Bulletin</hi> of <date when="1939-03-01">March 1, 1939</date>, gives the average annual<lb/>
               salary of $573. This seems to represent a fairly substantial gain over<lb/>
               <date when="1934">1934</date>-<date when="1935">35</date>, but it is true that there has been an increase in the cost of<lb/>
               living that would affect this gain to a great extent. It is our opin<lb break="no"/>
               ion that the increase in salary has been off-set by the increase in<lb/>
               cost of living and has not increased the net income of <name type="place">Florida</name> Negro<lb/>
               teachers since <date when="1934">1934</date>-<date when="1935">35</date>.<lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="68" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_068.jpg"/>
            <p rend="indent">
               "This situation offers a distinct challenge to the people of<lb/>
               <name type="place">Florida</name> to place these public employees on such a salary that they<lb/>
               can have a decent standard of living and can prepare themselves for<lb/>
               and assume a place of leadership in the Negro race. Without it, we<lb/>
               will not be able to solve the difficult problems that face us in<lb/>
               <name type="place">Florida</name> and <name type="place">the South</name>."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               White teachers of the state receive salaries far below the<lb/>
               national average, but their individual earnings are more than double<lb/>
               those of Negro teachers. This discriminatory wage scale is common<lb/>
               throught <name type="place">the South</name>. In a test case, <date when="1940-06">June 1940</date>, the <name type="place">United States<lb/>
               Circuit Court of Appeals at Asheville, North Carolina</name>, gave an opinion<lb/>
               that differentials in salary scales "because of race or color" are<lb/>
               unlawful. It was estimated that the court's decision would add<lb/>
               $1,320,000 annually to the salaries of Negro teachers in that state<lb/>
               alone. The test case was brought about by a union of <name type="place">North Carolina</name><lb/>
               Negro teachers which had a membership of 5,000. Application of this<lb/>
               equalization order to the <name type="place">Florida</name> school system would raise teaching<lb/>
               from the least to one of the most remunerative Negro professions.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               The <date when="1935">1935</date> state census listed 43,108 Negroes of high school age<lb/>
               in <name type="place">Florida</name>, of whom 9,556 were enrolled in high schools during the<lb/>
               <date when="1937">1937</date>-<date when="1938">38</date> term. Less than five per cent of the Negro youth complete<lb/>
               their high school courses, largely due to the necessity for earning<lb/>
               a living at an early age and partly because of the inadequate school<lb/>
               facilities. Thirty counties do not have Negro high schools. Only<lb/>
               <pb n="69" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_069.jpg"/>
               five of the high school are accredited institutions, though two private<lb/>
               Negro colleges have high school departments on the accredited list.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               <name type="place">Florida</name> spends less on grammar and high schools, white and colored,<lb/>
               than the average state. Yet, in proportion to its income, which is<lb/>
               below the National level, <name type="place">Florida</name> exceeds the average. It is apparent<lb/>
               that attempts to improve the school system are held in check by the<lb/>
               low average income of <name type="place">Florida</name> citizens. Public schools are supported<lb/>
               by taxation, and, when incomes are low, taxes must be correspondingly<lb/>
               low.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               There are seven private colleges and one state college for Negroes.<lb/>
               The latter, most important and largest of all, is the <name type="place">Florida Agri<lb break="no"/>
               cultural and Mechanical College for Negroes</name>, located on a hilltop cam<lb break="no"/>
               pus at <name type="place">Tallahassee</name>. It has a faculty of more than forty and an annual<lb/>
               enrollment that exceeds one thousand students. Originally a vocational<lb/>
               school, it now has full liberal arts courses and graduate work is of<lb break="no"/>
               fered in some fields.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               <name type="person_group">The Negro Baptist Church</name> endows two colleges: <name type="place">the Normal and<lb/>
                  Industrial College at St. Augustine</name>, with an estimated annual enroll<lb break="no"/>
                     ment of about three hundred, and the <name type="place">Florida Memorial College at Live<lb/>
                        Oak</name> with about two hundred and fifty students. <name type="person_group">The Methodist Episco<lb break="no"/>
                     pal Church</name> has a junior college at <name type="place">Jacksonville</name>. Also at<lb/>
                     <name type="place">Jacksonville</name> is the school operated by the <name type="person_group">African Methodist Church</name>,<lb/>
               <name type="place">Edward Waters College<location><geo>30.343637 -81.683688</geo></location></name>. <name type="person_group">The Roman Catholic</name> and <name type="person_group">Protestant Episcopal</name><lb/>
                     <pb n="70" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_070.jpg"/>  
               churches conduct parochial schools at <name type="place">Tampa</name>, <name type="place">Miami</name>, <name type="place">Jacksonville</name>, and<lb/>
               <name type="place">Pensacola</name>.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               <hi rend="underline">The Arts</hi>. A small but highly talented group of <name type="person_group"><name type="place">Florida</name> Negroes</name><lb/>
               has earned fame in art, literature, and music. The state has produced<lb/>
               several Negro composers and orchestra leaders, at least one of whom<lb/>
               has become internationally famous. <name type="person">James Rosamond Johnson</name>, born in<lb/>
               <name type="place">Jacksonville</name> in <date when="1881">1881</date>, has written the musical scores for a number of<lb/>
               Broadway shows, as well as a light operetta and many popular songs.<lb/>
               Among the nest known of his compositions in <hi rend="underline"><title level="m">Under the Bamboo Tree</title>,</hi> a<lb/>
               great success early in the century. His <hi rend="underline"><title level="m">Lift Ev'ry Voice and Sing</title></hi> is <lb/>
               sung at every Negro patriotic gathering. A collection of his music,<lb/>
               <hi rend="underline"><title level="m">Rolling Along in Song</title></hi>, was published in <date when="1937">1937</date>.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               Choirs of unusual merit are found in a number of Negro churches<lb/>
               in the larger cities, and several school groups have won notice out<lb break="no"/>
               side the state. There are annual song festivals at two of the col<lb break="no"/>
               leges.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               In literature, <name type="place">Florida</name> has contributed two outstanding <name type="person_group">Negro-<lb/>
               Americans</name>. Foremost is <name type="person">James Weldon Johnson</name>, brother of <name type="person">Rosamond</name>,<lb/>
               whose <hi rend="underline">Autobiography of an Ex-Colored Man</hi> went into several editions.<lb/>
               For many years before his accidental death in <date when="1938">1938</date> <name type="person">Johnson</name> had held<lb/>
               an influential position in national Negro affairs. Gifted with many<lb/>
               talents, he was by turn a teacher, lawyer, poet, writer of musical<lb/>
               comedy lyrics, foreign diplomat, novelist, editor, orator, educator,<lb/>
               and race leader. <name type="person">Johnson</name>'s career is told entertainingly in his<lb/>
               <pb n="71" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_071.jpg"/>
               autobiography,<hi rend="underline">Along this Way</hi>, and his last book, <hi rend="underline">Negro Americans,<lb/>
                  What Now?</hi> surveys the history of Negroes in the <name type="nation">United States</name> and<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               An itinerant <name type="person_group">Baptist</name> preacher's daughter, <name type="person">Zora Neale Hurston</name>, is<lb/>
               <name type="place">Florida</name>'s second distinguished Negro writer. Born at <name type="place">Mandarin</name>, she<lb/>
               has a home in <name type="place">Eatonville</name>, and has resided in <name type="place">Harlem</name> where she first<lb/>
               gained prominence as a member of the Negro literati. A fine stylist,<lb/>
               her writing reflect an insight into Negro emotional life. She has<lb/>
               produced five books since <date when="1934">1934</date>--<hi rend="underline"><title level="m">Jonah's Gourd Vine</title></hi>, <hi rend="underline"><title level="m">Mules and Men</title></hi>,<lb/>
               <hi rend="underline"><title level="m">Their Eyes Were Watching God</title></hi>, <hi rend="underline"><title level="m">Tell My Horse</title></hi>, and <hi rend="underline"><title level="m">Man on a Mountain</title></hi>,<lb/>
               in the order named. The first two display a wide knowledge of<lb/>
               anthropology and folklore, the third is a dramatic novel of the<lb/>
               <name type="place">Everglades</name>, the fourth deals with ceremonial rites in <name type="nation">Haiti</name> and<lb/>
               <name type="nation">Jamaica</name>, and the last interprets the life of <name type="person">Moses</name>.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               Less famous for his writings than for his leadership, <name type="person">A. Philip<lb/>
                  Randolph</name> was born in <name type="place">Crescent City</name> and educated in <name type="place">Jacksonville</name><lb/>
               schools. He has edited several Negro periodicals, and in <date when="1917">1917</date> he<lb/>
               was jailed with <name type="person">Eugene Debs</name> for obstructing the war-time draft acts.<lb/>
               A commanding orator, <name type="person">Randolph</name> held in <date when="1940">1940</date> two major posts in the<lb/>
               Negro-American world--the presidencies of the <name type="person_group">National Negro Congress</name><lb/>
               and the <name type="person_group">International Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters</name>.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               Another preacher's daughter, <name type="person">Augusta Savage</name>, born in <name type="place">Green Cove<lb/>
               Springs</name>, is regarded as the world's greatest Negro sculptor. She<lb/>
               achieved success in spite of years of poverty, and indifference of<lb/>
               <pb n="72" facs="../images/ew_d5_1687_072.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
               the white and Negro public. Among her best-known works are <hi rend="underline"><name type="person"><title level="m">Henry M.<lb/>
                  Flagler</title></name></hi>, <hi rend="underline"><title level="m">The Urchin</title></hi>, and symbolic representation of <hi rend="underline"><title level="m">Lift Ev'ry Voice</title><lb/>
            and Sing</hi>, the Negro national anthem. The latter, executed in heroic<lb/>
               proportions, was commissioned by the <name type="place">New York</name> World's Fair. It is<lb/>
               a huge harp, cradled in the hand of God, and its chords are famous<lb/>
               Negro singers. <name type="person">Savage</name> gave the first <name type="place">Florida</name> exhibition of her work<lb/>
               at <name type="place">Jacksonville</name> in <date when="1940">1940</date>.<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
     </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
