<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="custom.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Chicago World's Fair</title>
            <author>Florida Motor Lines</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription, edition, and encoding</resp>
               <name>Bethany Jerger</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This document forms part of the project "Editing the Eartha M.M. White Archive" at the University of North Florida.</p>            
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <region>Florida</region>                  
                  <settlement>Jacksonville</settlement>                  
                  <repository>University of North Florida, Thomas G. Carpenter Library Special Collections and Archives</repository> 
                  <collection>Eartha M.M. White Collection</collection>
                  <idno>Folder S4, Item 2872</idno>                  
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc>
                     <p> Full half page from a newspaper, high-quality scan on legal-size white paper.</p>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
     </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <editorialDecl>
           <p>This file was transcribed and encoded according to the editorial criteria of the project "Editing the Eartha M.M. White Archive." Using the various options encoded within &lt;choice&gt; elements, this file enables the viewing of a diplomatic transcription and a regularized reading text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="1" facs="../images/ew_s4_2872_001.jpg"/><!-- Here is your first page break. You need to make the image name here match the name of your file -->
        
         <div>
            <head><name type="event">Chicago World's Fair</name><lb/>
               Excursion</head><lb/>
            <p>
               Round Trip <name type="place" subtype="city">Jacksonville</name> to <name type="place" subtype="city">Chicago</name><lb/>
               (Bus Fare only) ..................... $30.40<lb/>
               ALL-EXPENSE TOURS<lb/>
               <name type="place" subtype="city">Jacksonville</name> to <name type="place" subtype="city">Chicago</name>, 4 Full Days in Chicago<lb/> 
               (including round trip transportation)<lb/>
               $45.00<lb/> 
            </p>
            <p>
            Go any bus, return any time within 60-day limit.<lb/>
            (Get your friends to join your party)<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
            <div>
               <head rend="align(center) case(allcaps)">Sample round trip rates</head>
               <p>
            
              (Bus Fare only) TO <name type="place" subtype="city">CHICAGO</name><lb/>
          
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell><name type="place" subtype="city">Jacksonville</name> ............. $30.40 </cell>
                     <cell><name type="place" subtype="city">ST. AUGUSTINE</name> ............. 32.05 </cell>
                     <cell><name type="place" subtype="city">DAYTONA BEACH</name> ............. 34.20 </cell>
                     <cell><name type="place" subtype="city">LAKELAND</name> .................. 38.05 </cell> 
                    
                 </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell><name type="place" subtype="city">MIAMI</name> ............. $43.15 </cell>
                     <cell><name type="place" subtype="city">WEST PALM BEACH</name> .... 41.25</cell>
                     <cell><name type="place" subtype="city">ORLANDO</name> ............ 36.75<lb/></cell>
                     <cell><name type="place" subtype="city">TAMPA</name> .............. 38.05</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="center"><name type="place" subtype="city">ST. PETERSBURG</name> ............. 39.25</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         <div>
            <p rend="indent">
               This rate is good for 60 days on the <name type="company"> Florida Motor Lines </name> or affili-<lb/>
               ated lines going or coming from Chicago. To find out what 4 days in <lb/>
                  <name type="place" subtype="city">Chicago</name> will cost you from any city, add $15.00 to the rate from city<lb/>
               you desire to make the trip.<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
               <head rend="align(center) case(allcaps)">What is included in </head><lb/>
            <p rend="indent"> Four nights' room rent, 4 admissions to the <name type="event">World's Fair</name>, 4 round<lb/>
                  trips to the <name type= "place"> World's Fair Grounds</name>, 4 days' breakfasts and dinners, one <lb/>
               two-hour sight-seeing trip <name type="place" subtype="city">City of Chicago</name>, one free sight-seeing trip<lb/>
               inside the fair grounds. For those who wish to extend time of their <lb/>
               stay in <name type="place" subtype="city">Chicago</name> up to or within the 60-day limit, the expense for the<lb/>
               extended time on the all-expense tours will be figured on the same <lb/>
               basis as the four days all-expense tour.<lb/> 
            </p>
            <p>
               If you do not wish to take of the all-expense tour <lb/>
               arrangement, simply buy your round-trip ticket from <lb/>
               <name type="company">Florida Motor Line</name> and when you get to <name type="place" subtype="city">Chicago</name> go to <name type="address">Florida <lb/>
               Normal Headquarters, 4322 South Michigan Avenue, Apartment No. 1, <lb/>
               <name type="place" subtype="city">Chicago</name></name>, for assistance and information as to accomodations. <lb/>
            </p>
        </div>
         <div>
            
            <head> HOW TOURS MAY BE PAID FOR:</head><lb/> 
            <p>
               It is hardly believable that anyone will be able that anyone will be able to attend the <lb/>
               <name type="event">World's Fair Exposition</name> and be priviledged to enjoy the phenomenal <lb/>
               sights offered; travel in comfort and safety en route, and all at the <lb/>
               small costs for which we have worked out these Tours for you. <lb/> 
            </p>
       
            <p rend="indent">In addition to this, we have also arranged a plan whereby you <lb/>
            may make your reservation on either of the Tours for a payment of <lb/>
            Five Dollars, and pay the balance on weekly or monthly terms: Terms<lb/>
            to be made to suit your convenience as long as all Tours are paid for <lb/>
            in within two days of the day you select to leave. <lb/> 
            </p>
         </div>
       
         <div>
            <head rend="align(center) case(allcaps)">Save money by using our tours to the exposition</head><lb/>
            <p>Under our plan you can be assured in advance of the COMPLETE COST OF <lb/>
                YOUR VISIT TO <name type="place" subtype="city">CHICAGO</name> AND <name type="event">THE WORLD'S FAIR</name>; from the time you leave <lb/>
             your home city and until you return, practically all expenses down to the smallest <lb/>
             items are included, thus eliminating every worry that will mar your pleasure while <lb/>
             visiting this great city during the greatest exposition ever held. This assures you <lb/>
             of proper reservations during your entire trip without inconveniences to you or time <lb/>
             wasted in efforts to make these for yourself. Seventy million people are expected <lb/>
                to attend the <name type="event">World's Fair</name>. Sleeping and eating reservations are already being <lb/>
                reserved or have been contracted for. Those planning a visit to <name type="place" subtype="city">Chicago</name> without <lb/>
             reservation or accomidations run the risk of being imposed upon, of disappoint-<lb/>
             ment and a great inconvenience as well as unnecessary costs. Any one of our <lb/>
             Tours will assure you of comfort, convenience and economy and save you any trouble <lb/>
             whatsoever in making reservations <lb/>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">
            FOR THE CONVENIENCE OF OUR PATRONS WE INCLUDE IN THIS AN <lb/>
            APPLICATION BLANK WHICH CAN BE USED IN MAKING YOUR APPLICA- <lb/>
            TION AND RESERVATION FOR ONE OF THESE TOURS.<lb/> </p>
      
            <p rend="indent"> Do not delay, but send in your application TODAY so that you <lb/>
            can be assured of accommodations on this wonderful Tour and oppor- <lb/>
               tunity to see the <name type="event"> World's Fair</name> at a bargain price. <lb/> 
            </p>
         </div>
        
            <div>
               <head> A CLOSE STUDY OF THE MANY ADVANTAGES AND ACCOMMODATIONS</head> <lb/>
               <p>
            Our TOURS will disclose that the same accommodations and same entertain- <lb/>
            ment would cost an individual or group of individuals quite a large sum over the <lb/>
            costs charged for our TOURS. <lb/>
            FOR ANY ADDITIONAL INFORMATION OR PARTICULARS DESIRED <lb/>
            Wire or write to <name type= "company">The Florida Normal World Fair Tours</name>, <lb/>
            <name type="place" subtype="city">ST. Augustine, Fla.</name> Phone 611 <lb/>
            or <name type="place" subtype="address">Florida Nor. World Fair Headquarters, 4322 (Apartment 1) <lb/>
               South Michigan Avenue, Chicago, Ill.</name><lb/>
               </p>
            </div>
            
            
            <div><p>
               
            (Cut off here and fill in this application form and send to <name type="place" subtype="city">St. Augustine</name>) <lb/>
            </p>
            </div>
               <div> <head> Application Form </head><lb/>
               <p>
            Date................................................. <date when="1933">1933</date>
           <name type="address">To the Florida Nor, World Fair Tour Committee, <lb/>
            N.W. Collier, Chairman, <lb/>
              <name type="place" subtype="city">St. Augusustine, Fla. </name></name><lb/>
            Gentlemen: <lb/>
            Enclosed please find my check, money order, or cash for Five Dollars, for <lb/>
            which please make reservation for your ALL-EXPENSE TOUR........... Trip to <lb/>
            the <name type="event"> Chicago Exposition</name>. It is understood that this cash payment is to apply on the <lb/>
            purchase price of $.............. and that the balance of $............... I will pay <lb/>
       
            
            
            
             
            
         </p>
            </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
