<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="custom.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title><name type="place">Buffalo,<choice><abbr>N.Y.<expan>New York</expan></abbr></choice></name><date when="1922-07-14"></date></title>
            <author><name type="person">Mary B. Talbert</name></author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Encoded into XML and transcribed by</resp>
               <name>Chad Germany</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>This document forms part of the project "Editing the Eartha M.M. White Archive" at the University of North Florida.</p>            
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>USA</country>
                  <region>Florida</region>                  
                  <settlement>Jacksonville</settlement>                  
                  <repository>University of North Florida, Thomas G. Carpenter Library Special Collections and Archives</repository> 
                  <collection>Eartha M.M. White Collection</collection>
                  <idno>Folder Y2, Item 648</idno>                  
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc>
                     <p>The document is a 2 page letter printed on a 10" x 8" sheet of paper. Type has faded in several places, both pages appear to have been folded and there is a 1/2 cm tear on the top edge of the first page.</p>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
     </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <editorialDecl>
           <p>This file was transcribed and encoded according to the editorial criteria of the project "Editing the Eartha M.M. White Archive." Using the various options encoded within &lt;choice&gt; elements, this file enables the viewing of a diplomatic transcription and a regularized reading text.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <pb n="1" facs="White Collection - Folder Y2 - 648 001.jpg"/>
         <p>Dear Friend and Co-worker :-<lb/></p>
         <p>At the <name type="place">Newark</name>Conference of the <orgName><choice><abbr>N.A.C.P.</abbr><expan>National Association For The Advancement Of Colored People</expan></choice></orgName>, re-<lb/>
         cently, <name role="politician">Congressman</name><name type="person">Dyer</name>said, that if one million colored<lb/>
         people and white people got together and decide Lynching would<lb/>
         go, as well as other<choice><sic>undemocratin</sic><corr>undemocratic</corr></choice>things against the negro.<lb/></p>
         <p>Following this Convention, sixteen colored<lb/>
         women from five states formed themselves into a voluntary<lb/>
         <orgName>Executive Committee-Anti-Lynching-Crusaders</orgName>and decided to put on<lb/>
         an intense campaign for the purpose of uniting one million women<lb/>
         white and black to end lynching, mob violence and other undemo-<lb/>
         cratic practices against ourselves.<lb/></p>
         <p>This Committee met again Saturday <date when="1922-07-08"></date>,<lb/>
         and entered into an organization and decided to begin work. They<lb/>
         believed that one million women could be united, and they also,<lb/>
         believed that one million dollars could be raised.</p>
         <p>By unanimous vote, I was elected <name role="administrator">National Director</name>of this Campaign. I am writing you to see if you will<lb/>
         join in with us. I want you to be <name role="administrator">State Director</name>of your State.<lb/>
         As <name role="administrator">State Director</name>, your duties will be outlined.</p>
         <p>We have decided upon the month of <date when="1922-08">August</date>for<lb/>
         organization--<date when="1922-09">September</date>for instruction and <date when="1922-10">October for a reali-<lb/>
         zation of our intensive work.</date></p>
         <p>The million dollars is not the big thing, but<lb/>
         the prayers of a million women united to do God's work. This<lb/>
         is to be a Campaign of prayer and self sacrifice. <choice><orig>Wont</orig><corr>Won't</corr></choice> you join<lb/>
         in with us?</p>
         <p>If you will act as <name role="administrator">State Director</name>, please<lb/>
         communicate with me at once. Your first duty will be to send<lb/>
         me the name and address of a Key Woman in every city and town<lb/>
         in your State. If there are factions, - appoint two Key Women--<lb/>
         for once, let us get together. This Campaign means to unite<lb/>
         every fraternal and church woman--every one of us must be united<lb/>
         into one big sisterhood.</p>
         <p>Letters of instruction will follow your ac-<lb/>
         ceptance. This is to be the biggest campaign ever untaken by<lb/>
         colored women. Our object is to place money into the legistla-<lb/>
         tion now being carried on by the <orgName><abbr>N.A.A.C.P.</abbr><expan>National Association For The Advancement Of Colored People</expan></orgName>, to end lynching<lb/><pb/>
         and mob violence. We want to get out our stationary with your<lb/>
         name as <name role="administrator">State Director.</name></p>
         <p>Lose no time in answering this letter.</p>
         <p>Yours for a UNITED SISTERHOOD,<lb/></p>
         <p><note place="bottommargin"><name type="person">Mary B Talbert</name></note></p>
        
         
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
